<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../documentation/Schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech title="you_can_murder_a_liberator,_but_you_can't_murder_liberation" speaker="f_hampton" organization="black_panthers" date="1969-04-27" source="mia">
    <!--amz: source link https://www.marxists.org/archive/hampton/1969/04/27.htm-->
<section heading="intro">
<p>ALL POWER TO THE PEOPLE.</p>

<p>What we are basically going to be talking about today is what the <org group="police" op="0">pig</org> is doing to the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Panthers</org> all around the country. We are going to have to talk about what we are going to have to do about the repression that they are putting on the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org>. We are not worried about getting off it—let’s try to deal with it.</p>

    <p>We got to talk first of all about the main man. The main man in the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org>, the main man in the struggle today—in the United States, in Chicago, in Cuba and anywhere else—the main man in the liberation struggle is our Minister of Defense, and yours too, <person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person>. He’s the main man because the <set group="wealthy_elite">head of the imperialist octopus</set> lies right in this country and whoever is dealing with the <set group="wealthy_elite">head of the octopus</set> in this country is the main man. He’s in jail now. We must tell the world that <cause cat="unjust_trial"><person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> was tried by the <org group="police" op="0">pigs</org> and they found him guilty</cause>. He was tried by the people, who found him not guilty, and we say <policy cat="free_political_prisoners">let him go, let him free, because we find him not guilty</policy>. This is our relentless demand. We will not let up one day, we will not give up the struggle to liberate our Minister of Defense, <person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> and we will continue to <act cat="non-violence" subcat="protest">exert pressure on the power structure and constantly bombard them with the people’s demand</act> that <policy cat="free_political_prisoners"><person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> be set free</policy>.</p>

    <p>It was <person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> who taught us how the people learn. You learn by participation. When <person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> started out what did he do? He got a gun and he got <person name="b_seale">Bobby</person> and <person name="b_seale">Bobby</person> got a gun. <cause cat="inaction">They had a problem in the community because people was being run over—<set group="children">kids</set> were being run over—at a certain intersection.</cause>(1) What did the people do? The people <act cat="non-violence" subcat="protest">went down to the government to redress their grievances</act> and <cause cat="inaction">the government told them to go to hell : "We are not going to put no stoplights down there UNTIL WE SEE FIT."</cause> What did <person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> do? Did he go out and tell the people about the laws and write letters and try to propagandize ’em all the time? NO! Some of that’s good, but the masses of the people don’t read—that’s what I heard <person name="h_newton">Huey</person> say—they learn through observation and participation. Did he just say this? NO! So what did he do? He got him a shotgun, he got <person name="b_seale">Bobby</person> and he got him a hammer and went down to the corner. He gave <person name="b_seale">Bobby</person> the shotgun and told him <act cat="self-defense" subcat="arming">if any <org group="police" op="0">pig motherfuckers</org> come by blow his mother fuckin brains out</act>. What did he do? <act cat="non-violence" subcat="mutual-aid">He went to the corner and nailed up a stop sign</act>. No more accidents, no more trouble. And then he went back—another situation like that. <policy cat="publicity">What’d the people do? They looked at it, they observed</policy>; they didn’t get a chance to participate in it. <act cat="non-violence" subcat="education">Next time what’d they do? Same kind of problem came up. The PEOPLE got THEIR shotguns, got THEIR nine milimeters, got THEIR hammers. How’d they learn? They learned by observation and participation. They learned one thing. When there is a fire you gather round the fire.</act> <person name="h_newton">Huey</person> got a shotgun and everybody gathered round him and <person name="b_seale">Bobby</person>. <policy cat="publicity">They saw what was going on and they had a chance to participate in it</policy>. As the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard leader</policy> he taught the people about the power structure; he led the people down the correct road of revolution. What are we doing?</p></section>

<section heading="breakfast_for_children">
    <p><act cat="non-violence" subcat="mutual-aid">Our Breakfast for Children program is feeding a lot of <set group="children">children</set></act> and the people understand our Breakfast for Children program. We sayin’ something like this—we saying that theory’s cool, but theory with no practice ain’t shit. You got to have both of them—the two go together. We have a theory about feeding kids free. What’d we do? We put it into practice. That’s how people learn. A lot of people don’t know how serious the thing is. They think the <set group="children">children</set> we feed ain’t really hungry. I don’t know five year old <set group="children">kids</set> that can act well, but I know that if they not hungry we sure got some actors. We got five year old actors that could take the academy award. Last week they had a whole week dedicated to the hungry in Chicago. <cause cat="need">Talking ’bout the starvation rate here that went up 15%. Over here where everybody should be eating.</cause> Why? Because of capitalism.</p>

    <p>What are we doing? <act cat="non-violence" subcat="mutual-aid">The Breakfast for Children program</act>. We are running it in a socialistic manner. <policy cat="publicity">People came and took our program, saw it in a socialistic fashion not even knowing it was socialism. People are gonna take our program and tell us to go on to a higher level.</policy> They gonna take that program and work it in a socialistic manner. What’d the <org group="police" op="0">pig</org> say? He say, "Nigger—you like communism?" "No sir, I’m scared of it." "You like socialism?" "No Sir, I’m scared of it." "You like the breakfast for children program?" "Yes sir, I’d die for it". <org group="police" op="0">Pig</org> said, "Nigger, that program is a socialistic program." "I don’t give a fuck if it’s Communism. <act cat="self-defense">You put your hands on that program motherfucker and I’ll blow your motherfucking brains out</act>." And he knew it. <act cat="non-violence" subcat="education">We been educating him, not by reading matter, but through observation and participation.</act> By letting him come n and work our program. Not theory and theory alone, but theory and practice. The two go together. We not only thought about the Marxist-Leninist theory—we put it into practice. This is what the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> is about.</p></section>

<section heading="subversives">
    <p>Some people talk a lot about communism, but the people can’t understand and progress to the stage of communism right away or because of abstract arguments. They say you got to crawl before you can walk. And the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org>, as the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard party</policy>, thought that the <act cat="non-violence" subcat="mutual-aid">Breakfast for Children Program</act> was the best technique of crawling that any <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard party</policy> could follow. And we got a whole lot of folks that’s going to be walking. And then a whole lot of folks that’s gonna be running. And when you got that, what you got? You got a whole lot of <org group="police" op="0">PIGS</org> that’s gonna be running. That’s what our program’s about.</p>

    <p>    <org group="black_panthers" op="5">The Black Panther Party</org> is about the <act cat="active-resistance" subcat="com-revolution">complete revolution</act>. We not gonna go out there and half do a thing. And you can let the <org group="police" op="0">pigs</org> know it. They come here and hide—they so uncomfortable they sitting on a taperecorder, they got their gun in their hair—they got to hide all this shit and they come here and do all this weird action. All they got to do is come up to 2350 West Madison any day of the week and anybody up there’ll let them know, let the motherfucker know: Yes, we subversive. Yes, we subversive with the bullshit we are confronted with today. Just as subversive as anybody can be subversive. <cause cat="police_disguises">And we think them motherfuckers is the <set group="criminals">criminals</set>. They the ones always hiding. We the ones up in front. We’re out in the open, <policy cat="police_visibility">these motherfuckers should start wearing uniforms</policy>. They want to know if the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Panthers</org> are goin’ underground—these motherfuckers IS underground. You can’t find ’em. People calls the <org group="police" op="0">pigs</org> but nobody knows where they at. They’re out chasing us. They hiding—can’t nobody even see ’em.</cause></p>

    <p>When people got a problem they come to the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> for help and that’s good. Because, like <person name="m_zedong">Mao</person> says, we are supposed to be ridden by the people and <person name="h_newton">Huey</person> says we’re going to be ridden down the path of <act cat="active-resistance" subcat="com-revolution">social revolution</act> and that’s for the people. The people ought to know that the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> is one thousand percent for the People. They write a lot of articles, you know, niggers’ll run up to you in a minute—when I say niggers I mean <set group="white_people">white niggers</set> and <set group="black_people">black niggers</set> alike—niggers’ll run up to you and talk that shit about, Man, I read in the Tribune today. Well you say, Man, fuck it right there. If you didn’t read it in <act cat="non-violence" subcat="newspaper">the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">BLACK PANTHER</org> paper, in the MOVEMENT</act>—then you ain’t read shit.</p></section>

<section heading="mickey_white">
    <p>We in the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> have another brother I want to take some time to rap about. This brother is constantly on our mind. This brother’s name is <person name="m_white">Michael White—Mickey White</person>. This brother is beautiful. <cause cat="unjust_trial">He’s being held now in jail for one hundred thousand dollars bail. Some of you who listen to the radio might have heard about brothers in the state chapter, our field secretary of Defense Captain, brother <person name="n_junior">Nathaniel Junior</person> and Brother <person name="m_harvey">Merrill Harvey</person> being laid up on some phoney gun charge.</cause> We don’t say the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Panthers</org> don’t want guns, but <act cat="self-defense" subcat="arming">we already got guns</act> and we don’t have to go and try and steal or connive to buy any guns from anybody. What they are trying to do is to squash out the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org>—they’re trying to squash out the leadership. Trying to squash out <person name="b_rush">Bobby Rush</person>, the Deputy Minister of Defense. Trying to squash out <person name="c_walls">Chaka</person> and <person name="c_brooks">Che</person>, the Deputy Minister of Education.</p>

<p>    <person name="m_white">Mickey White</person> was in that bullshit with <person name="n_junior">Nathaniel Junior</person> and <person name="m_harvey">Merrill Harvey</person>. Last week when they went to court even the judge in court said, you all gonna get a fair trial whether you deserve it or not. These are the types of actions we are confronted with. <person name="m_white">Mickey White</person> is <cause cat="unjust_trial">in solitary confinement and doesn’t get to come out of his cell for anything at any time. And he might be in that cell for the rest of his life. His bond is $100,000. That’s $10,000 cash.</cause></p>

    <p>    <person name="m_white">Mickey White</person> is a proven revolutionary. He’s not nobody we THINK is going to be a revolutionary. He’s not nobody we trying to make a revolutionary. He’s a proven revolutionary. All of you have to understand that <person name="m_white">Mickey White</person> is a <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Panther</org> in ideology, he’s a <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Panther</org> in word and he’s a <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Panther</org> in deed. He’s a <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Panther</org> that understands <policy cat="class_solidarity">it’s a class struggle—not a race question</policy>. You have to understand the pressures the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> goes through saying this. You can see the pressures the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> goes through by making a coalition with <set group="white_people">whites</set>.</p>

    <p>When the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> stood up and said we not going to fight racism with racism <org group="us_organization" op="1">US</org> said "NO, we can’t do that because it’s a race question and if you make it a class question then the revolution might come sooner. We in <org group="us_organization" op="1">US</org> ain’t prepared for no revolution because we think that power grows from the sleeve of a Dashiki." They are armed with rhetoric and rhetoric alone. And we found that when you’re armed with rhetoric and rhetoric alone a lot of times you get yourself hurt. <person name="e_cleaver">Eldridge Cleaver</person> told them, even though you say you fight fire with fire best, we think you fight fire with water. You can do either one, but we choose to fight with water. He said, we’re not going to fight racism with racism, <policy cat="class_solidarity">we’re going to fight racism with solidarity</policy>. Even though you think you ought to <cause cat="capitalist-injustice">fight capitalism with black capitalism</cause>, <policy cat="com-revolution">we’re going to fight capitalism with socialism</policy>.</p>

    <p>We got a whole lot of people being busted and you don’t even know about all these people. There’s one here you definitely have to know about and that’s our Deputy Minister of Defense—<person name="b_rush">Bobby Rush</person>. <cause cat="unjust_trial">Our Deputy Minister <person name="b_rush">Bobby Rush</person> was busted on some bullshit with a gun thing. He’s got three gun charges. He’s been convicted of one with a six month lead.</cause> He’s out on appeal now. <act cat="non-violence" subcat="defense-fund">I know a lot of you people say, well goddamn, you got a <person name="m_white">Mickey White</person> defense fund, an <person name="e_cleaver">Eldridge Cleaver</person> defense fund, a <person name="m_harvey">Merrill Harvey</person> defense fund, a <person name="n_junior">Nathaniel Junior</person> defense fund, a <person name="h_newton">Huey Newton</person> defense fund, a <person name="f_hampton">Fred Hampton</person>, <person>Jule</person>, <person name="c_brooks">Che</person>, and <person name="c_walls">Chaka</person> defense fund—and I just can’t keep up with all these defense funds. But since we are the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard party</policy> we try to do things right, so we got one defense fund so you don’t get mixed up on what name to send it to. We’ll decide who it goes to. You can just send it to Political Defense Fund</act>, 2350 West Madison. If you want to send something to <act cat="non-violence" subcat="mutual-aid">Breakfast for Children</act>, you can send it to 2350 West Madison also, and you can earmark that money to go to the <act cat="non-violence" subcat="mutual-aid">Breakfast for Children program</act>.</p>

    <p>We got <person name="m_white">Mickey</person> on our mind tonight—and everybody knows we got <person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> on our mind tonight. <cause cat="political_imprisonment">We got <set group="pol_prisoners">every political prisoner</set> in jail on our mind tonight.</cause> <person name="e_cleaver">Eldridge Cleaver</person>—<cause cat="unjust_trial">all of these people either dead, or in exile or in jail</cause>. A lot of people under­ standing this will lose real faith in the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard by</policy> not understanding what we’re talking about.</p>

    <p>A lot of these people will go up to you in a minute and say, "Why all these people being taken, why haven’t they shot it out with some <org group="police" op="0">pigs</org>." Well, what do we say? If you kill a few, you get a little satisfaction. But when you can kill them ALL you get complete satisfaction. That’s why we haven’t moved. We have to organize the people. <act cat="non-violence" subcat="education">We have to educate the people.</act> <act cat="self-defense" subcat="arming">We have to arm the people.</act> <act cat="active-resistance" subcat="com-revolution">We have to teach them about revolutionary political power. And when they understand all that we won’t be killing no few and getting no little satisfaction, we’ll be killing ’em all and getting complete satisfaction.</act></p></section>

<section heading="go_with_the_people">
    <p>So what should we do if we’re the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard</policy>? What is it right to do? Is it right for the <set group="revol_leaders">leadership of that struggle</set> to go faster than the <set group="revolutionaries">followers of that struggle</set> can go? NO! We’re not going to be dealing in commandism, we’re not going to be dealing in no tailism. We say that just as fast as the people can possibly go, that’s just as fast as we can take it.</p>

    <p>While we take it we must be sure that we are not missing the <set group="poor">people in the valley</set>. In the valley we know that we can learn to understand the life of the people. We know that with all the bullshit out there, you can come to consider yourself on the mountain top. I may even consider myself one day on the mountaintop. I may have already. But I know that in the valley there are people like <person name="b_xx">Benny</person> and there are people like me, people like <person name="m_white">Mickey White</person> and people like <person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> and <person name="b_seale">Bobby Seale</person>. And that below the valley are people like <person name="b_hutton">Bobby Hutton</person>, people like <person name="e_cleaver">Eldridge Cleaver</person>. We know that going into the valley is a dangerous thing. We know that when you go out to the valley you got to make a commitment.</p>

    <p>A lot of people think the revolution is bullshit, but it’s not. A lot of us think that when you get in the revolution you can talk your way out of things, but that’s not true. Ask <person name="b_hutton">Bobby Hutton</person>, ask <person name="h_newton">Huey Newton</person>, ask <person name="e_cleaver">Eldridge Cleaver</person>, <person name="m_white">Mickey White</person> and <person name="d_mora">Dennis Mora</person>. Ask these people whether it’s a game. If you get yourself involved in a revolutionary struggle then you’ve got to be serious. You got to know what you’re doing. You got to already have practiced some type of theory. That’s the reason we ask people to follow the <set group="revol_leaders">leadership</set> of the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard party</policy>. Because we all theorizing and we all practicing. We make mistakes, but we’re always correcting them and we’re always getting better.</p>

    <p>We used to run around yellin ’bout Panther Power—the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Panthers</org> run it. <policy cat="fix_mistakes">We admit we made mistakes. Our ten point program is in the midst of being changed right now, because <policy cat="class_solidarity">we used the word "white" when we should have used the word "capitalist"</policy>. We’re the first to admit our mistakes. We no longer say Panther Power because we don’t believe the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Panthers</org> should have all the power.</policy> We are not for the dictatorship of the Panthers. We are not for the dictatorship of <set group="black_people">Black people</set>. We are for the dictatorship of the people.</p>

<p>The difference between the people and the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard</policy> is very important. You got to understand that the people follow the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard</policy>. You got to understand that the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> IS the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard</policy>. If you are about going to the people you got to understand that the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard</policy> leads the people. After the social revolution, the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard party</policy>, through our <act cat="non-violence" subcat="education">educational programs—and that program is overwhelming—the people are educated to the point that they can run things themselves. That’s what you call educating the people</act>, organizing the people, <act cat="self-defense" subcat="arming">arming the people</act> and <act cat="active-resistance" subcat="com-revolution">bringing them revolutionary political power. That means people’s power. That means the people’s revolution. And if you’re not about being involved in a people’s revolution then you got to do something. You got to support the people’s revolution.</act></p></section>

<section heading="complete_satisfaction">
    <p>The <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> is the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard party</policy>. You better get on the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org>. If you can’t get on, goddamit you better get behind. If you can’t get behind goddamit, you better get behind somebody else so you’ll at least be able to follow indirectly, motherfucker. We ain’t asking you to go out and ask no <org group="police" op="0">pig</org> to leave us alone. We know that the <org group="police" op="0">pigs</org> fuck with us cause they know we’re doing something.</p>

    <p>Cause <set group="armchair_theorists">a lot of dudes</set> walk around and write articles about it. I know some <set group="revol_orgs">revolutionary groups</set> say these niggers are runnin around saying these things—the <org group="progressive_labor" op="0">PL</org>(2) motherfuckers talking that bullshit, couldn’t even find things to criticize. They was so far in the ground. What was they doing? Organizing groundhogs, educating groundhogs, arming groundhogs and teaching groundhogs revolutionary political power.</p>

    <p>I say that <policy cat="publicity">we’re the first group to come above ground where the people can follow you and see you. And if you make a mistake it’s better than not even being at all. When I made that mistake I made it for the people, and I correct it for the people</policy>. You don’t hear there was a raid on <org group="progressive_labor" op="1">PL</org>’s office last night. You ain’t never heard that. When you hear of <org group="progressive_labor" op="1">PL</org> busted in New York, <org group="progressive_labor" op="1">PL</org>’s leader in jail with no bars, <org group="progressive_labor" op="1">PL</org> leader run out of the country, <org group="progressive_labor" op="1">PL</org> leader shot 18 times while he was running with his back turned and hands tied up, <org group="progressive_labor" op="2">PL</org> leader gets <act cat="non-violence" subcat="mutual-aid">breakfast for children for 1800 people a week</act>. You ever hear it? Ya never heard it. I want to hear it. If you do hear it, it’ll be because of the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther</org> lead. I’m not putting all these things out and saying <org group="progressive_labor" op="3">PL</org> doesn’t know ’em. But I’m saying that when <set group="armchair_theorists">people</set> write something like this, a lot of people don’t understand it. And I wanted to take the time to explain it.</p>

<p>There are some things that <org group="progressive_labor" op="3">PL</org> says that are valid. Don’t misunderstand me. We don’t get mad because in some way or another <org group="progressive_labor" op="3">PL</org> is trying to better the <org group="black_panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> by trying to criticize it. But I just want to let you know, ain’t nothing all right and ain’t nothing all wrong. <policy cat="fix_mistakes">We’re not all right—though we trying to get that way. We make mistakes but we understand that we gonna make some more mistakes. And we gonna try and correct these mistakes and we gonna try and keep on moving.</policy></p>

<p>So what do we say? Don’t get the <org group="police" op="0">pigs</org> offa us cause we can stand em. We jail <person name="m_white">Mickey White</person>, we should let em murder <person name="b_hutton">Bobby Hutton</person>, we should let em run <person name="e_cleaver">Eldridge Cleaver</person> out of the country. Why? Because you can jail a revolutionary, but you can’t jail the revolution. You can run a freedom fighter around the country but you can’t run freedom fighting around the country. You can murder a liberator, but you can’t murder liberation.</p>

    <p>Kill a few and get a little satisfaction. Kill some more and you get some more satisfaction. Kill ’em all and you get complete satisfaction. <policy cat="class_solidarity">We say All Power to the People—Black Power to <set group="black_people">Black People</set> and Brown Power to <set group="brown_people">Brown People</set>, Red Power to <set group="AIAN">Red People</set> and Yellow Power to <set group="asian_people">Yellow People</set>. We say White Power to <set group="white_people">White People</set> EVEN. And we say Panther Power to the <policy cat="bpp_vanguardism">vanguard Party</policy></policy> and we say don’t kill a few and don’t kill some more. As a matter of fact we rather you didn’t move until you see we ready to move, and when you see we ready to move you know we not dealing with a few, we not dealing with some more. <act cat="active-resistance" subcat="com-revolution">You know that when we get ready to move we dealing from complete—that’s what we’re after—total, everything, everybody—complete satisfaction.</act></p>

<p>POWER TO THE PEOPLE</p></section>
</speech>
