<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../documentation/Schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech  title="i've_been_to_the_mountaintop" speaker="MLK" organization="NVM" date="1968-04-03" source="blackpast">
<p>
(1968) MARTIN LUTHER KING, JR., “I’VE BEEN TO THE MOUNTAINTOP”
</p>
<p>

Excerpt from Dr. Martin Luther King’s Last Sermon,
“I’ve Been to the Mountaintop,” Mason Temple,
Memphis, Tennessee, April 3, 1968.
</p>
 <p>
    Thank you very kindly, my friends. As <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> listened to <person name="ralph_abernathy" occupation="cr_leader">Ralph Abernathy</person> and his eloquent and generous introduction and then thought about myself, <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> wondered who he was talking about. It’s always good to have your closest friend and associate to say something good about you. And <person  name="ralph_abernathy" occupation="cr_leader">Ralph Abernathy</person> is the best friend that <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> have in the world. <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’m</person> delighted to see each of you here tonight in spite of a storm warning. You reveal that you are determined to go on anyhow.
</p><p>
    Something is happening in Memphis; something is happening in our world. And you know, if <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> were standing at the beginning of time, with the possibility of taking a kind of general and panoramic view of the whole of human history up to now, and <person name="god" occupation="god">the Almighty</person> said to me, “<person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">Martin Luther King</person>, which age would you like to live in?” I would take my mental flight by Egypt and I would watch  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person>’s children in their magnificent trek from the dark dungeons of Egypt through, or rather across the Red Sea, through the wilderness on toward the promised land. And in spite of its magnificence, <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> wouldn’t stop there.
</p><p>
    <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> would move on by Greece and take my mind to Mount Olympus. And I would see <person name="aristocles" occupation="philosopher">Plato</person>,<person name="aristotle" occupation="philosopher"> Aristotle</person>, <person name="socrates" occupation="philosopher">Socrates</person>,<person name="euripides" occupation="playwright"> Euripides</person> and <person name="aristophanes" occupation="playwright">Aristophanes</person> assembled around the Parthenon. And I would watch them around the Parthenon as they discussed the great and eternal issues of reality. But <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> wouldn’t stop there.
</p><p>
I would go on, even to the great heyday of the Roman Empire. And I would see developments around there, through various emperors and leaders. But I wouldn’t stop there.
</p><p>
I would even come up to the day of the Renaissance, and get a quick picture of all that the Renaissance did for the cultural and aesthetic life of man. But I wouldn’t stop there.
</p><p>
    I would even go by the way that the man for whom I am named had his habitat. And I would watch <person name="martin_luther" occupation="religious_leader">Martin Luther</person> as he tacked his ninety-five theses on the door at the church of Wittenberg. But I wouldn’t stop there.?
</p><p>
    I would come on up even to 1863, and watch a vacillating President by the name of <person name="abe_Lincoln" occupation="civil_servant">Abraham Lincoln</person> finally come to the conclusion that he had to sign the Emancipation Proclamation. But I wouldn’t stop there.
</p><p>
I would even come up to the early thirties, and see a man grappling with the problems of the bankruptcy of his nation. And come with an eloquent cry that we have nothing to fear but “fear itself.” But I wouldn’t stop there.
</p><p>
    Strangely enough, I would turn to <person name="god" occupation="god">the Almighty</person>, and say, “If you allow me to live just a few years in the second half of the 20th century, I will be happy.”?
</p><p>
    Now that’s a strange statement to make, because the world is all messed up. The nation is sick. Trouble is in the land; confusion all around. That’s a strange statement. <policy cat="hope">But I know, somehow, that only when it is dark enough can you see the stars.</policy> And I see  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person> working in this period of the twentieth century in a way that men, in some strange way, are responding. ?
</p><p>
    Something is happening in our world. The masses of people are rising up. And wherever they are assembled today, whether they are in Johannesburg, South Africa; Nairobi, Kenya; Accra, Ghana; New York City; Atlanta, Georgia; Jackson, Mississippi; or Memphis, Tennessee — the cry is always the same: <cause cat="freedom">“We want to be free.”</cause>?
</p><p>
    And another reason that  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’m</person> happy to live in this period is that we have been forced to a point where we are going to have to grapple with the problems that men have been trying to grapple with through history, but the demands didn’t force them to do it. Survival demands that we grapple with them. Men, for years now, have been talking about war and peace. But now, no longer can they just talk about it. It is no longer a choice between violence and nonviolence in this world; it’s <policy cat="non-violence">nonviolence or nonexistence.</policy> That is where we are today.??And also in the human rights revolution, if something isn’t done, and done in a hurry, to bring the colored peoples of the world out of their long years of poverty, their long years of hurt and neglect, the whole world is doomed. Now, I’m just happy that  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person> has allowed me to live in this period to see what is unfolding. And  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’m</person> happy that He’s allowed me to be in Memphis.?
</p><p>
    I can remember — I can remember when <set group="afro-american" type="race">Negroes</set> were just going around as <person name="ralph_abernathy" occupation="cr_leader">Ralph</person> has said, so often, scratching where they didn’t itch, and laughing when they were not tickled. But that day is all over. We mean business now, and we are determined to <cause cat="equality">gain our rightful place</cause> in  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person>’s world.??
</p><p>
    And that’s all this whole thing is about. We aren’t engaged in any negative protest and in any negative arguments with anybody. <cause cat="equality">We are saying that we are determined to be men.</cause> We are determined to be people. We are saying — We are saying that we are  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person>’s children. And that we are  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person>’s children, we don’t have to live like we are forced to live.??
</p><p>
    Now, what does all of this mean in this great period of history? It means that we’ve got to stay together. <cause cat="unity">We’ve got to stay together and maintain unity. </cause>You know, whenever Pharaoh wanted to prolong the period of slavery in Egypt, he had a favorite, favorite formula for doing it. What was that? He kept the slaves fighting among themselves. But whenever the slaves get together, something happens in Pharaoh’s court, and he cannot hold the slaves in slavery. When the slaves get together, that’s the beginning of getting out of slavery. Now let us maintain unity.??
</p><p>
    Secondly, let us keep the issues where they are. The issue is injustice.<cause cat="fairness"> The issue is the refusal of Memphis to be fair and honest in its dealings with its public servants, who happen to be sanitation workers.</cause> Now, we’ve got to keep attention on that. That’s always the problem with a little violence. You know what happened the other day, and the press dealt only with the window-breaking. I read the articles. They very seldom got around to mentioning the fact that one thousand, three hundred sanitation workers are on strike, and that Memphis is not being fair to them, and that <person name="harry_loeb" occupation="politician">Mayor Loeb</person> is in dire need of a doctor. They didn’t get around to that.
</p><p>
    <act cat="non=violence" subcat="march">Now we’re going to march again, and we’ve got to march again,</act> in order to put the issue where it is supposed to be — and force everybody to see that there are thirteen hundred of  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person>’s children here suffering, sometimes going hungry, going through dark and dreary nights wondering how this thing is going to come out. That’s the issue. And we’ve got to say to the nation: We know how it’s coming out. For when people get caught up with that which is right and they are willing to sacrifice for it, there is no stopping point short of victory.?
</p><p>
    <policy cat="perseverance">We aren’t going to let any mace stop us.</policy> We are masters in our nonviolent movement in disarming police forces; they don’t know what to do. I’ve seen them so often. I remember in Birmingham, Alabama, when we were in that majestic struggle there, we would move out of the 16th Street Baptist Church day after day; by the hundreds we would move out. And <person name="bull_connor" occupation="civil_servant">Bull Connor</person> would tell them to send the dogs forth, and they did come; <act cat="non-violent" subcat="perseverance">but we just went before the dogs singing, “Ain’t gonna let nobody turn me around.”?</act>
</p><p>
    <person name="bull_connor" occupation="civil_servant">Bull Connor</person> next would say, “Turn the fire hoses on.” And as I said to you the other night, <person name="bull_connor" occupation="civil_servant">Bull Connor</person> didn’t know history. He knew a kind of physics that somehow didn’t relate to the transphysics that we knew about. And that was the fact that there was a certain kind of fire that no water could put out. <act cat="non-violent" subcat="perseverance">And we went before the fire hoses; we had known water.</act> If we were <set group="baptist" type="church">Baptist</set> or some other denominations, we had been immersed. If we were <set group="baptist" type="church">Methodist</set>, and some others, we had been sprinkled, but we knew water. That couldn’t stop us.?
</p><p>
    And we just went on before the dogs and we would look at them; and <act cat="non-violent" subcat="perseverance">we’d go on before the water hoses and we would look at it, and we’d just go on singing “Over my head I see freedom in the air.” And then we would be thrown in the paddy wagons, and sometimes we were stacked in there like sardines in a can.</act> And they would throw us in, and old  <person name="bull_connor" occupation="civil_servant">Bull</person> would say, “Take ’em off,” and they did; and we would just go in the paddy wagon singing, “We Shall Overcome.” And every now and then we’d get in jail, and we’d see the jailers looking through the windows being moved by our prayers, and being moved by our words and our songs. And there was a power there which <person name="bull_connor" occupation="civil_servant">Bull Connor</person> couldn’t adjust to; and so we ended up transforming  <person name="bull_connor" occupation="civil_servant">Bull</person> into a steer, and we won our struggle in Birmingham. Now we’ve got to go on in Memphis just like that. I call upon you to be with us when we go out Monday.?
</p><p>
    Now about injunctions: We have an injunction and <act cat="non-violent" subcat="legal_action">we’re going into court tomorrow morning to fight this illegal, unconstitutional injunction.</act> All we say to America is, “Be true to what you said on paper.” <policy cat="anti-totalitarianism">If I lived in China or even Russia, or any totalitarian country, maybe I could understand some of these illegal injunctions.</policy> Maybe I could understand the denial of certain basic First Amendment privileges, because they hadn’t committed themselves to that over there. But somewhere I read of the freedom of assembly. Somewhere I read of the freedom of speech. Somewhere I read of the freedom of press. Somewhere I read that the greatness of America is the right to protest for right. And so just as I say, we aren’t going to let dogs or water hoses turn us around, we aren’t going to let any injunction turn us around. We are going on.??
</p><p>
We need all of you. And you know what’s beautiful to me is to see all of these ministers of the Gospel. It’s a marvelous picture. Who is it that is supposed to articulate the longings and aspirations of the people more than the preacher? Somehow the preacher must have a kind of fire shut up in his bones. And whenever injustice is around he tell it. Somehow the preacher must be an Amos, and saith, “When  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person> speaks who can but prophesy?” Again with Amos, “Let justice roll down like waters and righteousness like a mighty stream.” Somehow the preacher must say with <person name="god" occupation="god">Jesus</person>, “The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, because he hath anointed me,” and he’s anointed me to deal with the problems of the poor.”?
</p><p>
    And I want to commend the preachers, under the leadership of these noble men: <person name="james_lawson" occupation="cr_leader">James Lawson</person>, one who has been in this struggle for many years; he’s been to jail for struggling; he’s been kicked out of <org group="vanderbiltU" type="education" op="1">Vanderbilt University</org> for this struggle, but he’s still going on, fighting for the rights of his people. <person name="ralph_jackson" occupation="cr_leader">Reverend Ralph Jackson</person>,<person name="billy_kiles" occupation="cr_leader"> Billy Kiles</person>; <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> could just go right on down the list, but time will not permit. But <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I </person>want to thank all of them. And I want you to thank them, because so often, preachers aren’t concerned about anything but themselves. And I’m always happy to see a relevant ministry.?
</p><p>
    It’s all right to talk about “long white robes over yonder,” in all of its symbolism. But ultimately people want some suits and dresses and shoes to wear down here! It’s all right to talk about “streets flowing with milk and honey,” but  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person> has commanded us to be <policy cat="welfare">concerned about the slums down here, and his children who can’t eat three square meals a day.</policy>It’s all right to talk about the new Jerusalem, but one day,  <person name="god" occupation="god">God's</person> preacher must talk about the new New York, the new Atlanta, the new Philadelphia, the new Los Angeles, the new Memphis, Tennessee. This is what we have to do.?
</p><p>
    Now the other thing we’ll have to do is this: Always anchor our external direct action with the power of economic withdrawal. Now, we are poor people. Individually, we are poor when you compare us with white society in America. We are poor. Never stop and forget that collectively — that means all of us together — collectively we are richer than all the nations in the world, with the exception of nine. Did you ever think about that? After you leave the United States, Soviet Russia, Great Britain, West Germany, France, and I could name the others, the American <set group="afro-american" type="race">Negro</set> collectively is richer than most nations of the world. We have an annual income of more than thirty billion dollars a year, which is more than all of the exports of the United States, and more than the national budget of Canada. Did you know that? <act cat="active_resistance" subcat="mutualism">That’s power right there, if we know how to pool it. ?</act>
</p><p>
    <policy cat="non-violence">We don’t have to argue with anybody. We don’t have to curse and go around acting bad with our words. We don’t need any bricks and bottles. We don’t need any Molotov cocktails.</policy> We just need to go around to these stores, and to these massive industries in our country, and say, “ <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person> sent us by here, to say to you that you’re not treating his children right. And we’ve come by here to ask you to make the first item on your agenda fair treatment, where  <person name="god" occupation="god">God's</person> children are concerned. Now, if you are not prepared to do that, we do have an agenda that we must follow. And our agenda calls for withdrawing economic support from you.”?
</p><p>
    And so, as a result of this, we are asking you tonight, to go out and<act cat="non-violent" subcat="boycott"> tell your neighbors not to buy</act> <org group="coca-cola" type="company" op="1">Coca-Cola</org> in Memphis. Go by and tell them not to buy <org group="sealtest_diary" type="company" op="1">Sealtest</org> milk. Tell them not to buy — what is the other bread? — <org group="continental_baking" type="company" op="1">Wonder Bread</org>. And what is the other bread company, <person name="jesse_jackson" occupation="cr_leader">Jesse</person>? Tell them not to buy <org group="hart's_bakery" type="company" op="1">Hart’s bread</org>. As <person name="jesse_jackson" occupation="cr_leader">Jesse Jackson</person> has said, up to now, <act cat="non-violent" subcat="cooperate">only the garbage men have been feeling pain; now we must kind of redistribute the pain.</act> We are choosing these companies because they haven’t been <cause cat="fairness">fair in their hiring policies;</cause> and we are choosing them because they can begin the process of saying they are going to support the needs and the rights of these men who are on strike. And then they can move on town — downtown and tell <person name="harry_loeb" occupation="politician">Mayor Loeb</person> to do what is right.?
</p><p>
    But not only that, we’ve got to strengthen black institutions. <act cat="non-violent" subcat="boycott">I call upon you to take your money out of the banks downtown and deposit your money</act> in <org group="tri-state" type="company" op="4">Tri-State Bank</org>. <policy cat="black-owned">We want a “bank-in” movement in Memphis.</policy> Go by the savings and loan association. I’m not asking you something that we don’t do ourselves at <org group="sclc" type="cr_org" op="5">SCLC</org>. <person  name="benjamin_hooks" occupation="cr_leader">Judge Hooks</person> and others will tell you that we have an account here in the savings and loan association from the <org group="sclc" type="cr_org" op="5">Southern Christian Leadership Conference</org>. We are telling you to follow what we are doing. Put your money there. <policy cat="black-owned">You have six or seven black insurance companies here in the city of Memphis. Take out your insurance there. We want to have an “insurance-in.”?</policy>
Now these are some practical things that we can do. We begin the process of building a greater economic base. And at the same time, we are putting pressure where it really hurts. I ask you to follow through here. ?
</p><p>
    Now, let me say as I move to my conclusion that we’ve got to give ourselves to this struggle until the end. Nothing would be more tragic than to stop at this point in Memphis. <act cat="non-violence" subcat="march">We’ve got to see it through. And when we have our march, you need to be there. If it means leaving work, if it means leaving school — be there. Be concerned about your brother. You may not be on strike. But either we go up together, or we go down together.??</act>
</p><p>
Let us develop a kind of dangerous unselfishness. One day a man came to <person name="god" occupation="god">Jesus</person>, and he wanted to raise some questions about some vital matters of life. At points he wanted to trick <person name="god" occupation="god">Jesus</person>, and show him that he knew a little more than <person name="god" occupation="god">Jesus</person> knew and throw him off base….?
</p><p>
    Now that question could have easily ended up in a philosophical and theological debate. But <person name="god" occupation="god">Jesus</person> immediately pulled that question from mid-air, and placed it on a dangerous curve between Jerusalem and Jericho. And he talked about a certain man, who fell among thieves. You remember that a Levite and a priest passed by on the other side. They didn’t stop to help him. And finally a man of another race came by. He got down from his beast, decided not to be compassionate by proxy. But he got down with him, administered first aid, and helped the man in need. <person name="god" occupation="god">Jesus</person> ended up saying, this was the good man, this was the great man, because he had the capacity to project the “I” into the “thou,” and to be <cause cat="unity">concerned about his brother.?</cause>
</p><p>
Now you know, we use our imagination a great deal to try to determine why the priest and the Levite didn’t stop. At times we say they were busy going to a church meeting, an ecclesiastical gathering, and they had to get on down to Jerusalem so they wouldn’t be late for their meeting. At other times we would speculate that there was a religious law that “One who was engaged in religious ceremonials was not to touch a human body twenty-four hours before the ceremony.” And every now and then we begin to wonder whether maybe they were not going down to Jerusalem — or down to Jericho, rather to organize a “Jericho Road Improvement Association.” That’s a possibility. Maybe they felt that it was better to deal with the problem from the causal root, rather than to get bogged down with an individual effect.?
</p><p>
    But I’m going to tell you what my imagination tells me. It’s possible that those men were afraid. You see, the Jericho road is a dangerous road. I remember when <person>Mrs. King</person> and <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> were first in Jerusalem. We rented a car and drove from Jerusalem down to Jericho. And as soon as we got on that road, I said to my wife, “I can see why <person name="god" occupation="god">Jesus</person> used this as the setting for his parable.” It’s a winding, meandering road. It’s really conducive for ambushing. You start out in Jerusalem, which is about 1200 miles — or rather 1200 feet above sea level. And by the time you get down to Jericho, fifteen or twenty minutes later, you’re about 2200 feet below sea level. That’s a dangerous road. In the days of <person name="god" occupation="god">Jesus</person> it came to be known as the “Bloody Pass.” And you know, it’s possible that the priest and the Levite looked over that man on the ground and wondered if the robbers were still around. Or it’s possible that they felt that the man on the ground was merely faking. And he was acting like he had been robbed and hurt, in order to seize them over there, lure them there for quick and easy seizure. And so the first question that the priest asked — the first question that the Levite asked was, “If I stop to help this man, what will happen to me?” But then the Good Samaritan came by. And he reversed the question: <policy cat="unity">“If I do not stop to help this man, what will happen to him?”</policy>
</p><p>
That’s the question before you tonight. Not, “If I stop to help the sanitation workers, what will happen to my job. Not, “If I stop to help the sanitation workers what will happen to all of the hours that I usually spend in my office every day and every week as a pastor?” The question is not, “If I stop to help this man in need, what will happen to me?” The question is, “If I do not stop to help the sanitation workers, what will happen to them?” That’s the question.??
</p><p>
    Let us rise up tonight with a greater readiness. Let us stand with a greater determination. And let us move on in these powerful days, these days of challenge to make America what it ought to be. <cause cat="improvement"> We have an opportunity to make America a better nation.</cause> And  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> want to thank  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person>, once more, for allowing me to be here with you.?
</p><p>
    You know, several years ago,  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> was in New York City autographing the first book that  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> had written. And while sitting there autographing books, a demented black woman came up. The only question I heard from her was, “Are you <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">Martin Luther King</person>?” And I was looking down writing, and I said, “Yes.” And the next minute I felt something beating on my chest. Before  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> knew it  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> had been stabbed by this demented woman.  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> was rushed to Harlem Hospital. It was a dark Saturday afternoon. And that blade had gone through, and the X-rays revealed that the tip of the blade was on the edge of my aorta, the main artery. And once that’s punctured, your drowned in your own blood — that’s the end of you.??
</p><p>
    It came out in the <org group="New_York_Times" type="company" op="2">New York Times</org> the next morning, that if  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> had merely sneezed, <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> would have died. Well, about four days later, they allowed me, after the operation, after my chest had been opened, and the blade had been taken out, to move around in the wheel chair in the hospital. They allowed me to read some of the mail that came in, and from all over the states and the world, kind letters came in.  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I </person>read a few, but one of them  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I </person> will never forget.  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I </person> had received one from the <person name="dwight_eisenhower" occupation="politician"> President</person> and the  <person name="richard_nixon" occupation="politician">Vice-President</person>. I’ve forgotten what those telegrams said. I’d received a visit and a letter from the  <person name="nelson_rockefeller" occupation="politician">Governor of New York</person>, but I’ve forgotten what that letter said. But there was another letter that came from a little girl, a young girl who was a student at the White Plains High School. And I looked at that letter, and I’ll never forget it. It said simply, ?
</p><p>
    Dear  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">Dr. King</person>,
</p><p>
    "I am a ninth-grade student at the <org group="white_plains_high" type="education" op="2">White Plains High School</org>."
</p><p>
And she said, ??
</p><p>
    "While it should not matter,  I would like to mention that I’m a white girl. I read in the paper of your misfortune, and ?of
your suffering. And I read that if you had sneezed, you would have died. And I’m simply writing you to say that? I’m so
happy that you didn’t sneeze."
</p><p>
    And  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> want to say tonight —  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> want to say tonight that  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I </person>too am happy that  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I </person>didn’t sneeze. Because if  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> had sneezed,  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> wouldn’t have been around here in 1960, when students all over the South started sitting-in at lunch counters. And  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> knew that as they were sitting in, they were really standing up for the best in the American dream, and taking the whole nation back to those great wells of democracy which were dug deep by the <set group="founders" type="political_faction">Founding Fathers</set> in the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution.?
</p><p>
    If  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I </person>had sneezed,  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> wouldn’t have been around here in 1961, when we decided to take a ride for freedom and ended segregation in inter-state travel.?
</p><p>
    If  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> had sneezed,  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> wouldn’t have been around here in 1962, when <set group="afro-american" type="race">Negroes</set> in Albany, Georgia, decided to straighten their backs up. And whenever men and women straighten their backs up, they are going somewhere, because a man can’t ride your back unless it is bent.?
</p><p>
    If  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> had sneezed — If  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> had sneezed  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> wouldn’t have been here in 1963, when the black people of Birmingham, Alabama, aroused the conscience of this nation, and brought into being the Civil Rights Bill.?
</p><p>
    If  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I </person>had sneezed,  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> wouldn’t have had a chance later that year, in August, to try to tell America about a dream that  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> had had.?
</p><p>
    If  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> had sneezed,  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> wouldn’t have been down in Selma, Alabama, to see the great Movement there.?
</p><p>
    If  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> had sneezed,  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> wouldn’t have been in Memphis to see a community rally around those brothers and sisters who are suffering. ?
</p><p>
    <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’m</person> so happy that  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> didn’t sneeze.?
</p><p>
    And they were telling me –. Now, it doesn’t matter, now. It really doesn’t matter what happens now. I left Atlanta this morning, and as we got started on the plane, there were six of us. The pilot said over the public address system, “We are sorry for the delay, but we have  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">Dr. Martin Luther King</person> on the plane. And to be sure that all of the bags were checked, and to be sure that nothing would be wrong with on the plane, we had to check out everything carefully. And we’ve had the plane protected and guarded all night.”??And then I got into Memphis. And some began to say the threats, or talk about the threats that were out. What would happen to me from some of our sick white brothers. Well, I don’t know what will happen now. We’ve got some difficult days ahead. <policy cat="determination">But it really doesn’t matter with me now,</policy> because  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’ve</person> been to the mountaintop.
</p><p>
    And  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> don’t mind.
</p><p>
    Like anybody,  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> would like to live a long life. Longevity has its place. But  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’m</person> not <policy cat="determination">concerned about that now.</policy>  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> just want to do  <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person>’s will. And He’s allowed me to go up to the mountain. And  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’ve</person> looked over. And  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’ve</person> seen the Promised Land.  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> may not get there with you. But  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I</person> want you to know tonight, that we, as a people, will get to the promised land!
</p><p>
    And so  <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’m</person> happy, tonight.
</p><p>
    <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’m</person> not worried about anything.??
</p><p>
    <person name="MLK" occupation="cr_leader">I’m</person> not fearing any man! ??
</p><p>
    Mine eyes have seen the glory of the coming of the <person name="god" occupation="god">Lord</person>!!
</p>
<citation>
Citation:
BlackPast, B. (2007, September 29). (1968) Martin Luther King, Jr., “I’ve Been to the Mountaintop”. BlackPast.org. https://www.blackpast.org/african-american-history/1968-martin-luther-king-jr-i-ve-been-mountaintop/
Sources:
homas R. West and James W. Mooney eds., To Redeem A Nation: A History and Anthology of the Civil Rights Movement (New York: Brandywine Press, 1993), pp. 86-88.
</citation>
</speech>
