<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../documentation/Schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech title="the_women's_liberation_and_gay_liberation_movements" speaker="h_newton" organization="black_panthers" date="1970-08-15" source="mia">
    <!--amz: source link https://www.blackpast.org/african-american-history/speeches-african-american-history/huey-p-newton-women-s-liberation-and-gay-liberation-movements/-->
    <p>During the past few years strong movements have developed among <set group="women">women</set> and among <set group="lgbtq">homosexuals</set> seeking their liberation. There has been some uncertainty about how to relate to these movements.</p>

    <p>Whatever your personal opinions and your insecurities about homosexuality and the various liberation movements among <set group="lgbtq">homosexuals</set> and <set group="women">women</set> (and I speak of the <set group="lgbtq">homosexuals</set> and <set group="women">women</set> as <set group="oppressed">oppressed groups</set>), we should try to unite with them in a revolutionary fashion. I say "whatever your insecurities are" because as we very well know, sometimes our first instinct is to want to hit a homosexual in the mouth and want a woman to be quiet. We want to hit a homosexual in the mouth because we are afraid that we might be homosexual; and we want to hit the woman or shut her up because we are afraid that she might castrate us or take the nuts that we might not have to start with.</p>

    <p>We must gain security in ourselves and therefore <policy cat="intersectional_solidarity">have respect and feelings for all <set group="oppressed">oppressed people</set></policy>. We must not use the racist attitude that the <set group="racists">White racists</set> use against <set group="black_people">our people</set> because they are Black and poor. Many times the poorest White person is the most racist because he is afraid that he might lose something, or discover something that he does not have. So you're some kind of a threat to him. This kind of psychology is in operation when we view <set group="oppressed">oppressed people</set> and we are angry with them because of their particular kind of behavior, or their particular kind of deviation from the established norm.</p>

    <p>Remember, we have not established a revolutionary value system; <policy cat="fix_mistakes">we are only in the process of establishing it</policy>. I do not remember our ever constituting any value that said that a revolutionary must say offensive things towards <set group="lgbtq">homosexuals</set>, or that a revolutionary should make sure that <set group="women">women</set> do not speak out about their own particular kind of oppression. <policy cat="intersectional_solidarity">As a matter of fact, it is just the opposite: we say that we recognize the <set group="women">women</set>'s right to be free. We have not said much about the homosexual at all, but we must relate to the <set group="lgbtq">homosexual movement</set> because it is a real thing. And I know through reading, and through my life experience and observations that <set group="lgbtq">homosexuals</set> are not given freedom and liberty by anyone in the society. They might be the most oppressed people in the society.</policy></p>

    <p>And what made them homosexual? Perhaps it's a phenomenon that I don't understand entirely. Some people say that it is the decadence of capitalism. I don't know if that is the case; I rather doubt it. But whatever the case is, we know that homosexuality is a fact that exists, and we must understand it in its purest form: that is, <policy cat="intersectional_solidarity">a person should have the freedom to use his body in whatever way he wants.</policy></p>

    <p>That is not endorsing things in homosexuality that we wouldn't view as revolutionary. But there is nothing to say that a homosexual cannot also be a revolutionary. <policy cat="fix_mistakes">And maybe I'm now injecting some of my prejudice by saying that "even a homosexual can be a revolutionary."</policy> Quite the contrary, maybe <policy cat="intersectional_solidarity">a homosexual could be the most revolutionary</policy>.</p>

    <p>When we have <act cat="active-resistance" subcat="com-revolution">revolutionary conferences</act>, <act cat="non-violence" subcat="protest">rallies, and demonstrations</act>, <policy cat="intersectional_solidarity">there should be full participation of the <set group="lgbtq">gay liberation movement</set> and the <set group="women">women's liberation movement</set>.</policy> Some groups might be more revolutionary than others. We should not use the actions of a few to say that they are all reactionary or counterrevolutionary, because they are not.</p>

    <p>We should deal with the factions just as we deal with <set group="revol_orgs">any other group or party that claims to be revolutionary</set>. <policy cat="vetting">We should try to judge, somehow, whether they are operating in a sincere revolutionary fashion and from a really oppressed situation. (And we will grant that if they are <set group="women">women</set> they are probably oppressed.) If they do things that are unrevolutionary or counterrevolutionary, then criticize that action.</policy> <policy cat="fix_mistakes">If we feel that the group in spirit means to be revolutionary in practice, but they make mistakes in interpretation of the revolutionary philosophy, or they do not understand the dialectics of the social forces in operation, we should criticize that and not criticize them because they are women trying to be free. And the same is true for <set group="lgbtq">homosexuals</set>. We should never say a whole movement is dishonest when in fact they are trying to be honest. They are just making honest mistakes. Friends are allowed to make mistakes.</policy> The enemy is not allowed to make mistakes because his whole existence is a mistake, and we suffer from it. But <policy cat="intersectional_solidarity">the <set group="women">women's liberation front</set> and <set group="lgbtq">gay liberation front</set> are our friends</policy>, they are our potential allies, and <policy cat="build_alliances">we need as many allies as possible.</policy></p>

    <p><policy cat="overcome_bias">We should be willing to discuss the insecurities that many people have about homosexuality. When I say "insecurities," I mean the fear that they are some kind of threat to our manhood. I can understand this fear. Because of the long conditioning process that builds insecurity in the <set group="us_men">American male</set>, homosexuality might produce certain hang-ups in us.</policy> I have hang-ups myself about male homosexuality. But on the other hand, I have no hang-up about female homosexuality. And that is a phenomenon in itself. I think it is probably because male homosexuality is a threat to me and female homosexuality is not.</p>

    <p><policy cat="overcome_bias">We should be careful about using those terms that might turn our friends off.</policy> <policy cat="fix_mistakes">The terms "faggot" and "punk" should be deleted from our vocabulary, and especially we should not attach names normally designed for <set group="lgbtq">homosexuals</set> to <set group="oppressors">men who are enemies of the people</set>, such as Nixon or Mitchell.</policy> <set group="lgbtq">Homosexuals</set> are not enemies of the people.</p>

    <p><policy cat="intersectional_solidarity">We should try to form a working coalition with the <set group="lgbtq">gay liberation</set> and <set group="women">women's liberation groups</set>.</policy> We must always handle social forces in the most appropriate manner.</p>
</speech>