<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speech title="i_have_a_dream" speaker="MLK" organization="SCLC" date="1963-08-28" source="blackpast" >
(1963) MARTIN LUTHER KING JR., “I HAVE A DREAM”
    <Section heading="">
        
        <p> I am happy to join with you today  in what will go down in history as the greatest
            <act cat="non-violence" subcat="gathering">demonstration </act> for freedom in the history of our nation. Five score years ago, a great
            <person name="Abraham Lincoln">American</person>, in whose symbolic shadow
            we stand, <act cat="law" subcat="civil-rights">signed the Emancipation Proclamation</act>. This momentous decree came as a great
            beacon light of hope to millions of <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> slaves had been seared in the flames of
            withering <policy cat="injustice">injustice</policy>. It came as a joyous daybreak to end the long night of captivity. </p>
        <p> But one hundred years later, we must face the tragic fact that the <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> is still <policy cat="injustice">not
            free</policy>. One hundred years later, the life of the <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> is still sadly crippled by the
            manacles of segregation and the chains of <policy cat="discrimination">discrimination</policy>. One hundred years later, the
            <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> lives on a <policy cat="inequality">lonely island of poverty in the midst of a vast ocean of material
            prosperity</policy>. One hundred years later the <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> is still languishing in the comers of
            <org name="american" type="nationality">American</org> society and finds <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">himself</org> an <policy cat="inequality">exile in his own land</policy>. <act cat="non-violence" subcat="demostration">So we have come here today
                to dramatize an appalling condition.</act> </p>
        <p> In a sense we have come to our nation’s capital to cash a check. When the <org name="founders" type="pol_org">architects</org> of
            our republic <act cat="law" subcat="civil_rights">wrote the magnificent words of the Constitution and the Declaration of
                Independence</act>, they were signing a <act cat="non-violence" subcat="promise">promissory note</act> to which every <org name="american" type="nationality">American</org> was to fall
            heir. This note was a promise that all men would be guaranteed the unalienable rights of
            life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness. </p>
        <p> It is obvious today that America has defaulted on this promissory note insofar as her
            citizens of color are concerned. Instead of honoring this sacred obligation, America has
            given the <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> people a bad check; a check which has come back marked “insufficient
            funds.” But we refuse to believe that the bank of justice is bankrupt. We refuse to
            believe that there are insufficient funds in the great vaults of opportunity of this
            nation. So we have come to cash this check a check that will give us <cause cat="equality">upon demand the
                riches of freedom and the security of justice</cause>. We have also come to this hallowed spot
            to remind America of the fierce urgency of now. This is no time to engage in the luxury
            of cooling off or to take the tranquilizing drug of gradualism. Now is the time to make
            real the promises of democracy. Now is the time to <cause cat="equality">rise from the dark and desolate
                valley of segregation to the sunlit path of racial justice</cause>. Now is the time to open the
            doors of opportunity to all of God’s children. Now is the time to lift our nation from
            the quicksands of racial injustice to the solid rock of brotherhood. </p>
        <p> It would be fatal for the nation to overlook the urgency of the moment and to
            underestimate the determination of the <group name="black" type="race"><org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org></group>.
            This sweltering summer of the <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org>’s legitimate discontent will not pass until there is
            an invigorating autumn of freedom and equality. Nineteen sixty three is not an end, but
            a beginning. Those who hope that the <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> needed to blow off steam and will now be
            content will have a rude awakening if the nation returns to business as usual. There
            will be neither rest nor try America until the <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> is granted his citizenship rights.
            The whirlwinds of revolt will continue to shake the foundations of our nation until the
            bright day of justice emerges. </p>
        <p> But there is something that I must say to my people who stand on the warm threshold
            which leads into the palace of justice. In the process of gaining our rightful place, we
            must not be guilty of wrongful deeds. <policy cat="non-violence">Let us not seek to satisfy our thirst for freedom
            by drinking from bitterness and hatred</policy>. We must forever conduct our struggle on the high
            plane of dignity and discipline. We must not allow our creative protest to degenerate
            into physical violence. Again and again we must rise to the majestic heights of meeting
            physical force with soul force. The marvelous new militancy which has engulfed the <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org>
            community <policy cat="racial_unity">must not lead us to a distrust of all white people, for many of our white
                brothers</policy>, as evidenced by their presence here today, have come to realize that their
            destiny is tied up with our destiny and their freedom is inextricable bound to our
            freedom. </p>
        <p> We cannot walk alone. </p>
        <p> And as we walk, we must make the pledge that we shall march ahead. We cannot turn back.
            There are those who are asking the devotees of civil rights, “When will you be
            satisfied?” We can never be satisfied as long as the <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> is the victim of the
            unspeakable <cause cat="police_brutality">horrors of police brutality</cause>. We can never be satisfied as long as our
            bodies, heavy with the fatigue of travel, cannot gain lodging in the motels of the
            highways and the hotels of the cities. We cannot be satisfied as long as the <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org>’s
            basic mobility is from a smaller ghetto to a larger one. We can never be satisfied as
            long as a <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> in Mississippi cannot vote and a <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> in New York believes he has
            nothing for which to vote. No, no, we are not satisfied, and will not be satisfied until
            justice rolls down like waters and righteousness like a mighty stream. </p>
        <p> I am not unmindful that some of you have come here out of great trials and tribulations.
            Some of you have come fresh from narrow <cause cat="false_imprisonment">jail cells</cause>. Some of you have come from areas
            where your quest for freedom left you battered by the storms of persecution and
            staggered by the winds of police brutality. You have been the veterans of creative
            suffering. Continue to work with the faith that unearned suffering is redemptive. </p>
        <p> Go back to Mississippi, go back to Alabama, go back to South Carolina, go back to
            Georgia, go back to Louisiana, go back to the slums and ghettos of our modern cities,
            knowing that somehow this situation can and will be changed. Let us not wallow in the
            valley of despair. </p>
        <p> I say to you today my friends, that in spite of the difficulties and frustrations of the
            moment I still have a dream. It is a dream deeply rooted in the <org name="american" type="nationality">American</org> dream. </p>
        <p> I have a dream that one day this nation will rise up and live out the true meaning of
            its creed: “We hold these truths to be self evident; that all men are created equal.” </p>
        <p> I have a dream that one day on the red hills of Georgia the sons of former slaves and
            the sons of former slave owners will be able to sit down together at the table of
            brotherhood. </p>
        <p> I have a dream that one day even the state of Mississippi, a desert state sweltering in
            the heat of injustice and oppression, will be transformed into an oasis of freedom and
            justice. </p>
        <p> I have a dream that my four little children will one day live in a nation where they
            will not be judged by the color of their skin but by the content of their character. </p>
        <p> I have a dream today. </p>
        <p> I have a dream that one day the state of Alabama, whose governor’s lips are presently
            dripping with the words of interposition and nullification, will be transformed into a
            situation where little black boys and black girls will be able to join hands with little
            white boys and white girls and walk together as sisters and brothers. </p>
        <p> I have a dream today. </p>
        <p> I have a dream that one day every valley shall be exalted, every hill and mountain shall
            be made low, the rough places will be made plains, and the crooked places will be made
            straight, and the glory of the Lord shall be revealed, and all flesh shall see it
            together. </p>
        <p> This is our hope. This is the faith with which I return to the South. With this faith we
            will be able to hew out of the mountain of despair a stone of hope. With this faith we
            will be able to work transform the jangling discords of our nation into a beautiful
            symphony of brotherhood. With this faith we will be able to work together, to pray
            together, to struggle together, to go to jail together, to stand up for freedom
            together, knowing that we will be free one day. </p>
        <p> This will be the day when all of God’s children will be able to sing with meaning “My
            country ’tis of thee, sweet land of liberty, of thee I sing. Land where my fathers died,
            land of the pilgrim’s pride, from every mountainside, let freedom ring.” </p>
        <p> And if America is to be a great nation this must become true. So let freedom ring from
            the prodigious hilltops of New Hampshire. Let freedom ring from the mighty mountains of
            New York. Let freedom ring from the heightening Alleghenies of Pennsylvania! </p>
        <p> Let freedom ring from the snowcapped Rockies of Colorado. </p>
        <p> Let freedom ring from the curvaceous slopes of California! </p>
        <p> But not only that; let freedom ring from Stone Mountain of Georgia! </p>
        <p> Let freedom ring from Lookout Mountain of Tennessee! </p>
        <p> Let freedom ring from every hill and molehill of Mississippi. From every mountainside,
            let freedom ring. </p>
        <p> When we let freedom ring, when we let it ring from every village and every hamlet, from
            every state and every city, we will be able to speed up that day when all of God’s
            children, black men and white men, Jews and Gentiles, Protestants and Catholics, will be
            able to join hands and sing in the words of the old <org name="Afro-Americans" type="race">Negro</org> spiritual, “Free at last! Free
            at last! Thank God Almighty, we are free at last!” </p>

    </Section>

    <Citations> Citation: BlackPast, B. (2007, January 29). (1963) Martin Luther King Jr., “I Have a
        Dream”. BlackPast.org.
        https://www.blackpast.org/african-american-history/speeches-african-american-history/1963-martin-luther-king-jr-i-have-dream/
        Sources:William Safire, ed., Lend Me Your Ears: Great Speeches in History (W. W. Norton and
        Company: New York, 1992). </Citations>
</speech>
