<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speech  title="what's_your_name?" speaker="muhammad_ali" organization="nation_of_islam" date="1967-04-22" source="">
<p>(1967) Muhammad Ali, “Black is Best”
April 22, 1967</p>

<p>We are striving today for Freedom, Justice, and equality and as a matter of fact the Whole World is fighting for freedom, justice, and equality.
and I would like for you to know more about my leader and my teacher the Honorable <person  name="elijah_muhammad" occupation="religious_leader">Elijah Muhammad</person>. I'm signing autographs today too and we have newspaper here. Entitled <org group="muhammad_speaks" type="newspaper">Mohammed Speaks</org> newspapers and theses newspapers are sold for a cheap, cheap, price. And just 20 cents and you cannot buy the Wisdom, Knowledge, and understanding that's in this newspaper. And I would like to see as many of you as possible who can afford it. Buy one of these papers and I don't care if you buy 4,000 of them i'll be here unitl I sign every paper, everyone. If you just line up for miles I'll stay here and sin these papers. It's just that important for you and the money. I'm not here for the money as you know I'm averaging around 2 million a year.</p>
<!--gs:in this section, the Mr. Chang reference is someone who im not sure Ali is referring to, or is he is even referring to a person at all or if its just for the point of his speech. same goes for the end names at the end of this paragraph-->
    <p>You all are not crazy. You're not fools. You're intelligent. This is 1967. People are going to the Moon! Other countries that were slaves on the masters are  getting independence and if you check it donw get right down to it we don't who we are. What's your name? If I said it was <person name="unsure" occupation="unsure">Mr. Chang Chong</person>, you'd picture a <set name="chinese" type="ethnicity">Chinamen</set>. If I said here comes <person name="nikita_khruschev" occupation="politician">Mr. Khrushchev</person>, you'd look for a <set name="russian" type="ethnicity">Russian</set>. If I said in comes <person name="arthur_goldberg" occupation="statesman">Mr. Goldberg</person>, you look for <set group="jewish" type="religious_group">Jews</set>. If I said in comes <person name="Mew-hu-she-kaw" occupation="indigenous_chief">Whitecloud</person> you look for <set group="indigenous">Indian</set>. I said in comes <person name="fidel_castro" occupation="politician">Castro</person>, you look for a <set name="cuban" type="ethnicity">Cuban</set>. Here comes <person name="patrice_lumumba" occupation="prime_minister">Mr. Lumumba</person>, <person name="jomo_kenyatta" occupation="president">Mr Kenyatta</person> you look for  <set name="african" type="ethnicity">African</set>, a <set name="african" type="ethnicity">Black man</set>. Now what's your last name? If I said in comes <person>Mr. Jones</person>, <person>Mr. Hawkins</person>, <person>Mr. Clay</person>, <person>Mr. Culpepper</person>, <person>Mr. Roundtree</person>. You won't know if he's <set name="african" type="ethnicity">Black</set> or <set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> until you see him alright.</p>

<p>We are 22 Million people who don't have our names. We were named after our slave master, so teaches the Honorable <person name="elijah_muhammad" occupation="religious_leader">Elijah Muhammad</person>. 
When we were first brought to America. We were robed of all knowledge of ourselves. 
Mentally, we are not free, see, <person name="god" occupation="god">Jesus</person>, said "The Truth shall make you free". The Truth alone, you shall know the truth and that will make you free."
He didn't say setting in, laying in, walking in, forcing in, and integrating in truth. And once you become free, find out who you are, then you'll start saying "I am the Greatest </p>

<p>We look at Miss American, we see <set name="european" type="ethnicity">white</set>, we look at Miss World we see <set name="european" type="ethnicity">white</set>, we look at Miss Universe we see <set name="european" type="ethnicity">white</set>. Even Tarzan, the King of the Jungle, in back Africa.
    We can't got to heaven, we can't go to heaven until wer're washed in lamb blood to it's <set name="european" type="ethnicity">white</set> as snow.
When we get to heaven we walk on a Milky <set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> Way. We are taught, when we were little children that Mary had a little lamb, his feet as <set name="european" type="ethnicity">white</set> as snow. 
Then we were talking about Snow <set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set>.This is not funny, this is serious, it's a fact, a true fact.
<set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> Owl Cigars, <set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> Swan soap, King <set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> Soap,<set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> Cloud Tissue Paper, <set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> rain hairs, <set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> Tornado Flow Wax, <set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> plus two face. 
All the good cowboys around the <set name="european" type="ethnicity">white</set> horses. The <set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> House, ... Angel food cake is the <set name="european" type="ethnicity">white</set> cake but the Devil food cake is the Chocolate cake.
You feel better already if you're hearing this for the first time.</p>

<p>
"When the <set name="european" type="ethnicity"><set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> man</set> came to America, 
He neeeded someone to work the land 
his back was too weak he needed you <set name="african" type="ethnicity" >black man.</set> 
so he commissioned 
Sir <person name="john_hawkins" ocupation="slave_trader">John Hawkins</person> to commit world's 
most <act>griefest sin</act> that is take a man 
who's born to be free 
and bring him down to slavery sell a man 
as merchandise 
on his body put a price 
so my friends its easy to tell <set name="european" type="ethnicity">White</set> man's Heaven
is a <set name="african" type="ethnicity">black man</set>'s Hell"   
</p>

<citation>
Citation:
Afud101."Muhammad Ali Speech on Civil Rights." YouTube, Feb 13 2021,https://youtu.be/xPr5OkrBCM8</citation>
Transcription By:
Cole Ball
History Major at University of Pittsburgh-Greensburg <!--gs: when i try to put the end tag </citation> it gives me an error message. unsure how to fix-->
</speech>