<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speech  title="black_power" speaker="stokely_carmichael" organization="SNCC" date="1966-10-29" source="blackpast"> 
    <p>(1966) STOKELY CARMICHAEL, “BLACK POWER” </p>
    <p> It’s a privilege and an honor to be in
        the white intellectual ghetto of the West. This is a student conference, as it should be,
        held on a campus, and we’ll never be caught up in intellectual masturbation on the question
        of <cause cat="self-determination">Black Power</cause>. That’s the function of the people who are advertisers but call themselves
        reporters. Incidentally, for my friends and members of the press, my self-appointed white
        critics, I was reading <person name="bernard_shaw" occupation="writer" >Mr. Bernard Shaw</person> two days ago, and I came across a very important
        quote that I think is most apropos to you. <person name="bernard_shaw" occupation="writer" >He </person>says, “All criticism is an autobiography.” Dig
        yourself. Ok. </p>
    <p> The philosophers <person name="albert_camus" occupation="philosopher">Camus</person> and <person name="jean-paul_sartre" occupation="philosopher">Sartre</person> raise the
        question of whether or not a man can condemn himself. The <set group="black" type="race">black</set> existentialist philosopher
        who is pragmatic, <person name="frantz_fanon" occupation="philosopher">Frantz Fanon</person>, answered the question. He said that man could
        not. <person name="albert_camus" occupation="philosopher">Camus</person> and <person name="jean-paul_sartre" occupation="philosopher">Sartre</person> don’t answer the question. We in <org group="sncc" type="cr_org"> SNCC </org> tend to agree with <person name="frantz_fanon" occupation="philosopher">Fanon</person>–a man
        cannot condemn himself. If he did, he would then have to inflict punishment upon himself. An
        example is the <set group="nazi" type="political_party">Nazis</set>. Any of the <set group="nazi" type="political_party">Nazi</set> prisoners who, after he was caught and incarcerated,
        admitted that he committed crimes, that he killed all the many people he killed, had to
        commit suicide. The only ones able to stay alive were the ones who never admitted that they
        committed a crime against people–that is, the ones who rationalized that <set group="jews" type="religious_group">Jews</set> were not human
        beings and deserved to be killed, or that they were only following orders. There’s another,
        more recent example provided by the officials and the population–the <set group="european" type="race">white population</set> — of
        Neshoba County, Mississippi (that’s where Philadelphia is). They could not condemn <person name="lawrence_rainey" occupation="police_officer">Sheriff
            Rainey</person>, his deputies, and the other fourteen men who killed three human beings. They could
                not because they elected <person name="lawrence_rainey" occupation="police_officer">Mr. Rainey</person> to do precisely what he did; and condemning him would be
        condemning themselves.
    </p>
    <p> In a much larger view, <org group="sncc" type="cr_org">SNCC</org> says that <set group="european" type="race">white
        America</set> cannot condemn herself for her criminal acts against <set group="black" type="race">black America</set>. So
        <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> have done it–you stand condemned. <policy cat="critical_race_theory">The institutions that function in this
            country are clearly racist; they’re built upon racism.</policy> The questions to be dealt with then
        are: how can <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> inside this country move? How can <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> who say they’re not
        part of those institutions begin to move? And how then do we begin to clear away the
        obstacles that we have in this society, to make us live like human beings?
    </p>
    <p> Several
        people have been upset because we’ve said that integration was irrelevant when initiated by
        <set group="black" type="race">blacks</set>, and that in fact it was an insidious subterfuge for the maintenance of white
            supremacy. In the past six years or so, this country has been feeding us a “thalidomide drug
        of integration,” and some <set group="black" type="race">negroes</set> have been walking down a dream street talking about
        sitting next to <set group="european" type="race">white people</set>. That does not begin to solve the problem. We didn’t go to
        Mississippi to sit next to <person name="ross_barnett" occupation="politician">Ross Barnett</person> (former governor of Mississippi), we did not go to
            sit next to <person  name="james_clark" occupation="police_officer">Jim Clark</person> (sheriff of Selma, Alabama), we went to get them out of our
            way. People ought to understand that; we were never fighting for the right to integrate, <cause cat="anti-white_supremacy">we
            were fighting against white supremacy</cause>. In order to understand white supremacy, we must
        dismiss the fallacious notion that <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> can give anybody his freedom. A man is born
        free. You may enslave a man after he is born free, and that is in fact what this country
        does. It enslaves <set group="black" type="race">blacks</set> after they’re born. The only thing <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> can do is stop
        denying <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> their freedom. </p>
    
    <p> I maintain that every civil rights bill in this country was passed for <set group="european" type="race">white people</set>, not for <set group="black" type="race">black people</set>.
        For example, I am  <set group="black" type="race">black</set>. I know that. I also know that while I am  <set group="black" type="race">black</set> I am a human being.
        Therefore I have the right to go into any public place. <set group="european" type="race">White people</set> don’t know that. Every time I tried to go into a public
        place they stopped me. So some boys had to write a bill to tell that <set group="european" type="race">white man</set>, “He’s a
        human being; don’t stop him.” That bill was for the <set group="european" type="race">white man</set>, not for me. I knew <act cat="non-violence" subcat="vote">I could
            vote all the time and that it wasn’t a privilege but my right.</act> Every time I tried I was
        shot, killed or jailed, beaten or economically deprived. So somebody had to write a bill to
        tell <set group="european" type="race">white people</set>, “When a <set group="black" type="race">black man</set> comes to vote, don’t bother him.” That bill was for
        <set group="european" type="race">white people</set>. I know I can live anyplace I want to live. It is <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> across this
        country who are incapable of allowing me to live where I want. You need a civil rights bill,
        not me. The failure of the civil rights bill isn’t because of <cause cat="self-determination">Black Power</cause> or because of the
        <org group="sncc" type="cr_org">Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee </org> or because of the rebellions that are occurring in
        the major cities. That failure is due to the <set group="european" type="race">white’s</set> incapacity to deal with their own
        problems inside their own communities. And so in a sense we must ask, How is it that <set group="black" type="race">black
            people</set> move? And what do we do? But the question in a much greater sense is, How can <set group="european" type="race">white
            people</set> who are the majority, and who are responsible for making democracy work, make it
        work? They have never made democracy work, be it inside the United States, Vietnam, South
        Africa, the Philippines, South America, Puerto Rico, or wherever America has been.<act cat="non-violence" subcat="anti-war"> We not
        only condemn the country for what it has done internally, but we must condemn it for what it
        does externally. </act>We see this country trying to rule the world, and someone must stand up and
        start articulating that this country is not <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person>, and that it cannot rule the world. </p>
    
    <p>
        The white supremacist attitude, which you have either consciously or subconsciously, is
        running rampant through society today. For example, missionaries were sent to Africa with
        the attitude that <set group="black" type="race">blacks</set> were automatically inferior. As a matter of fact, the first act the
        missionaries did when they got to Africa was to make us cover up our bodies, because they
        said it got them excited. We couldn’t go bare-breasted any more because they got excited!
        When the missionaries came to civilize us because we were uncivilized, to educate us because
        we were uneducated, and to give us some literate studies because we were illiterate, they
        charged a price. The missionaries came with the Bible, and we had the land: When they left,
        they had the land, and we still have the Bible. That’s been the rationalization for Western
        civilization as it moves across the world–stealing, plundering, and raping everybody in its
        path. Their one rationalization is that the rest of the world is uncivilized and they are in
        fact civilized. </p>
    
    <p> But the West is un-civ-i-lized. And that still runs on today, you
        see, because now we have “modern-day missionaries,” and they come into our ghettos–they Head
        Start, Upward Lift, Bootstrap, and Upward Bound us into white society. They don’t want to
        face the real problem. A man is poor for one reason and one reason only–he does not have
        money. <policy cat="welfare">If you want to get rid of poverty, you give people money.</policy> And you ought not tell me
        about people who don’t work, and that you can’t give people money if they don’t work,
        because if that were true, you’d have to start stopping <person name="nelson_rockefeller" occupation="politician">Rockefeller</person>, <person name="bobby_kennedy" occupation="politician">Kennedy</person>, <person name="LBJ" occuaption="politician">Lyndon Baines
            Johnson</person>, <person name="lady_bird_johnson" occupation="wife">Lady Bird Johnson</person>, the whole of <org group="standard_oil" type="company">Standard Oil</org>, the  <org group="gulf_corp" type="company">Gulf Corporation </org>, all of them,
        including probably a large number of the board of trustees of <org group="uc_berkeley" type="education">this university</org>. The question,
        then, is not whether or not one can work; it’s Who has power to make his or her acts
        legitimate? That is all. In his country that power is invested in the hands of <set group="european" type="race">white people</set>,
        and it makes their acts legitimate.
        </p>
    
    <p> We are now engaged in a psychological struggle
        in this country about whether or not <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> have the right to use the words they want
        to use without <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> giving their sanction. We maintain the use of the words <cause cat="self-determination">Black
            Power</cause> — let them address themselves to that. We are not going to wait for <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> to
        sanction <cause cat="self-determination">Black Power</cause>. We’re tired of waiting; every time <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> try to move in this
        country, they’re <act cat="self-defense" subcat="status_movement">forced to defend their position beforehand.</act> It’s time that <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> do
        that. They ought to start defending themselves as to why they have oppressed and exploited
        us. A man was picked as a slave for one reason–the color of his skin. <set group="black" type="race">Black</set> was
        automatically inferior, inhuman,. And therefore fit for slavery, so the question of whether
        or not we are individually suppressed is nonsensical, and it’s a downright lie. We are
        oppressed as a group because we are <set group="black" type="race">black</set>, not because we are lazy or apathetic, not because
        we’re stupid or we stink, not because we eat watermelon or have good rhythm. We are
        oppressed because we are <set group="black" type="race">black</set>. 
    </p>
    <p> <cause cat="self-determination">In order to escape that oppression we must wield the
        group power we have,</cause> not the individual power that this country sets as the criterion under
        which a man may come into it. That’s what is called integration. “You do what I tell you to
        do and we’ll let you sit at the table with us.” Well, if you believe in integration, you can
        come live in Watts, send your children to the ghetto schools. Let’s talk about that. If you
        believe in integration, then we’re going to start adopting us some <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> to live in
        our neighborhoods. </p>
    
    <p> So it is clear that this question is not one off integration or
        segregation. We cannot afford to be concerned about the 6 percent <set group="black" type="race">black children</set> in this
        country whom you allow to enter white schools. <policy cat="concern_for_poor">We are going to be concerned about the 94
            percent. You ought to be concerned about them too.</policy> But are we willing to be concerned about
        the <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> who will never get to <org group="uc_berkeley" type="education">Berkeley</org>, never get to <org group="harvard" type="education">Harvard</org>, and cannot get an
        education, the ones you’ll never get a chance to rub shoulders with and say, “Why, he’s
        almost as good as we are; he’s not like the others”? The question is, How can white society
        begin to move to see <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> as human beings? I am <set group="black" type="race">black</set>, therefore I am. Not I am
        black and I must go to college to prove myself. I am black, therefore I am. And don’t
        deprive me of anything and say to me that you must go to college before you gain access to
        X, Y, and Z. That’s only a rationalization for suppression. </p>
    
    <p> The political parties of this country do not meet the needs of the people on a day-to-day basis.<cause cat="self-determination"> How can we build new
        political institutions that will become the political expressions of people?</cause> How can you
        build political institutions that will begin to meet the needs of Oakland, California? The
        need of Oakland, California, is not 1,000 <set group="police" type="law_enforcement">policemen</set> with submachine guns. They need that
        least of all. How can we build institutions that will <cause cat="representation">allow those people to function on a
        day-to-day basis, so that they can get decent jobs and have decent houses, and they can
        begin to participate in the policy and make the decisions that affect their lives?</cause> That’s
        what they need, not <set group="nazi" type="political_party">Gestapo troops</set>, because this is no 1942, and if you play like <set group="nazi" type="political_party">Nazis</set>,
        we’re not going to play <set group="jews" type="religious_group">Jew</set> this time around. </p>
    
    <p> Get hip to that. Can <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> move inside their own community and start tearing down racism where in fact it exists? It is you
        who live in Cicero and stopped us from living there. <set group="european" type="race">White people</set> stopped us from moving
        into Grenada, Miss. <set group="european" type="race">White people</set> make sure that we live in the ghettos of this country.
        <set group="european" type="race">White </set>institutions do that. They must change. In order for America to really live on a basic
        principle of human relationships, a new society must be born.<cause cat="anti-racism"> Racism must die.</cause> <cause cat="equity">The economic
        exploitation by this country</cause> of non-<set group="european" type="race">white people</set> around the world must also die. </p>
    <p>
        There are several programs in the South where whites are trying to organize poor whites so
        they can begin to move around the question of economic exploitation and political
        disfranchisement. We’ve all heard the theory several times. But few people are willing to go
        into it. The question is, Can the white activist stop trying to be a Pepsi generation who
        comes alive in the <set group="black" type="race">black community</set>, and be a man who’s willing to move into the white
        community and start organizing where the organization is needed? Can he do that? Can the
        white activist disassociate himself from the clowns who waste time parrying with each other
        and start talking about the problems that are facing people in this state? You must start
        inside the <set group="european" type="race">white community</set>. </p>
    
    <p> Our political position is that we don’t think the
    <org group="democratic_party" type="political_party">Democratic Party</org> represents the needs of <set group="black" type="race">black people</set>. We know that it does not. If, in
        fact, <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> believe that they’re going to move inside that structure, how are they
        going to organize around a concept of whiteness based on true brotherhood and on stopping
        economic exploitation in order to form a coalition base for <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> to hook up with?
        You cannot build a coalition based on national sentiment. If you want a coalition to address
        itself to real changes in this country, <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> must start building those institutions
        inside the <set group="european" type="race">white community</set>. And that’s the real question faction the white activists today.
        Can they tear down the institutions that have put us all in the trick bag we’ve been into
        for the last hundreds of years? </p>
    
    <p> <person name="frederick_douglass" occupation="writer">Frederick Douglass</person> said that the youth should fight to be leaders today. <person name="god" occupation="god">God</person> knows we need to be leaders today, because the men who run this
        country are sick. <cause cat="self-determination">We must begin to start building those institutions and to fight to
        articulate our position, to fight to be able to control our universities (we need to be able
        to do that), to fight to control the basic institutions that perpetuate racism by destroying
        them and building new ones.</cause> That’s the real question that faces us today, and it is a
        dilemma because most of us don’t know how to work.
    </p>
    <p> Most white activists run into the <set group="black" type="race">black community</set> as an excuse. We cannot have <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> working in the <set group="black" type="race">black community</set> —
        on psychological grounds. The fact is that all <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> question whether or not they are
        equal to whites, since every time they start to do something, <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> are around
        showing them how to do it. <cause cat="confidence"> we are going to eliminate that for the generation that comes
            after us, </cause>then <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> <act cat="non-violence" subcat="self-determination">must be in positions of power,</act> doing and articulating for
        themselves. That’s not reverse racism; it is moving onto healthy ground; it is becoming what
        the philosopher <person name="jean-paul_sartre" occupation="philosopher">Sartre</person> says, an “antiracist racist.” And this country can’t understand that.
        If everybody who’s white sees himself as racist and sees us against him, he’s speaking from
        his own guilt. </p>
    
    <p> 
        We do not have the power in our hands to change the institution of
        war in this country–to begin to recreate it so that they can learn to leave the <set group="vietnamese" type="ethnicity">Vietnamese
            people</set> alone. The only power we have is the power to say, <act cat="active-resistance" subcat="draft_dodge">“Hell, no!” to the draft</act>. 
    </p>
    <p>
        The war in Vietnam is illegal and immoral. The question is, <cause cat="anti-war">What can we do to stop that war?</cause>
        What can we do to stop the people who, in the name of America, are killing babies, women,
        and children? We have to say to ourselves that there’s a higher law than the law of a fool
        named <person name="dean_rusk" occupation="diplomat">Rusk</person>; there’s a higher law than the law of a buffoon named <person name="LBJ" occupation="politician">Johnson</person>. It’s the law of
        each of us. <policy cat="non-cooperation">We will not murder anybody who they say kill, and if we decide to kill, ‘were’
            going to decide who it shall be.</policy> This country will only stop the war in Vietnam when the
        young men who are made to fight it begin to say, <policy cat="non-cooperation">“Hell, no, we aren’t going.”</policy> </p>
    
    <p> The peace movement has been a failure because it hasn’t gotten off the college campuses where
        everybody has a 2S and is not afraid of being drafted anyway. The problem is how you can
        move out of that into the white ghettos of this country and articulate a position for those
        <set group="european" type="race">white youth</set> who do not want to go. You cannot do that. It is sometimes ironic that many of
        the peace groups have begun to call <org group="sncc" type="cr_org">SNCC</org> violent and they say they can no longer support us,
        when we are in fact the most militant organization for peace or civil rights or human rights
        against the war in Vietnam in this country today. 
    </p>
    <p> 
        There isn’t one organization that
        has begun to meet our stand on the war in Vietnam. We not only say we are <cause cat="anti-war">against the war in
            Vietnam</cause>; <policy cat="anti-draft">we are against the draft.</policy> No man has the right to take a man for two years and
        train him to be a killer. Any <set group="black" type="race">black man</set> fighting in the war in Vietnam is nothing but a
        <set group="black" type="race">black mercenary</set>. Any time a <set group="black" type="race">black man</set> leaves the country where he can’t vote to supposedly
        deliver the vote to somebody else, he’s a <set group="black" type="race">black mercenary</set>. Any time a <set group="black" type="race">black man</set> leaves this
        country, gets shot in Vietnam on foreign ground, and returns home and you won’t give him a
        burial place in his own homeland, he’s a <set group="black" type="race">black mercenary</set>. 
    </p>
    <p> 
        Even if I believed the lies of <person name="LBJ" occupation="politician">Johnson</person>, that we’re fighting to give democracy to the people of
        Vietnam, as a <set group="black" type="race">black man</set> living in this country <policy cat="anti-war">I wouldn’t fight to give this to anybody. </policy>We
        have to use our bodies and our minds in the only way that we see fit. We must begin, as the
        philosopher <person name="albert_camus" occupation="philosopher">Camus </person> says, to come alive by saying “no.” This country is a nation of thieves.
            It stole everything it has, beginning with <set group="black" type="race">black people</set>. The U.S. cannot justify its
        existence as the policeman of the world any longer. The marines are at ready disposal to
            bring democracy, and if the <set>Vietnamese</set> don’t want democracy, well then, “We’ll just wipe
        them out, because they don’t deserve to live if they won’t have our way of life.” 
    </p>
    <p>
        There is a more immediate question: What do you do on your campus? Do you raise questions
        about the hundred <set group="black" type="race">black students</set> who were kicked off campus a couple of weeks ago? Eight
        hundred? And how does that question begin to move? Do you begin to relate to people outside
        the ivory tower and university walls? Do you think you’re capable of building those human
        relationships based on humanity when the country is the way it is, when the institutions are
        clearly against us. 
    </p>
    <p> We have found all the myths of the country to be nothing but
        downright lies. We were told that if we worked hard we would succeed, and if that were true
        we would own this country lock, stock, and barrel. We have picked the cotton for nothing; we
        are the maids in the kitchens of liberal <set group="european" type="race">white people</set>; we are the janitors, the porters, the
        elevator men; we sweep up your college floors. We are the hardest workers and the lowest
        paid. It is nonsensical for people to talk about human relationships until they are willing
        to build new institutions. <set group="black" type="race">Black people</set> are economically insecure. White liberals are
        economically secure. Can you begin to build an economic coalition? Are the liberals willing
        to share their salaries with the economically insecure <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> they so much love? Then
        if you’re not, are you willing to start building new institutions that will provide economic
        security for <set group="black" type="race">black people</set>? That’s the question we want to deal with! 
    </p>
    
    <p> 
        American students are perhaps the most politically unsophisticated students in the world. 
    </p>
    
    <p>
        Across every country of the world, while we were growing up, students were leading the major
        revolutions of their countries. We have not been able to do that. They have been politically
        aware of their existence. In South America our neighbors have one every 24 hours just to
        remind us that they are politically aware. But we have been unable to grasp it because we’ve
        always moved in the field of morality and love while people have been politically jiving
        with our lives. You can’t move morally against men like <person name="edmund_brown?" occupation="politician">Brown</person> and <person name="ronald_reagan" occupation="politician">Reagan</person>. You can’t move
        morally against <person name="LBJ" occuaption="politician">Lyndon Baines Johnson</person> because he is an immoral man. He doesn’t know what
        it’s all about. So you’ve got to move politically. We have to develop a political
        sophistication that doesn’t parrot (“The two-party system is the best system in the world”).
        We have to raise questions about whether we need new types of political institutions in this
        country, and we in <org group="sncc" type="cr_org">SNCC</org> maintain that we need them now. Any time <person name="LBJ" occuaption="politician">Lyndon Baines Johnson</person> can
            head a party that has in it <person name="bobby_kennedy" occupation="politician">Bobby Kennedy</person>, <person name="wayne_morse" occupation="politician">Wayne Morse</person>, <person name="james_eastland" occupation="politician">Eastland</person>, <person name="william_wallace">Wallace</person>, and all those
        other <set>supposed-to-be-liberal cats</set>, there’s something wrong with that party. They’re moving
        politically, not morally. If that party refuses to seat <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> from Mississippi and
        goes ahead and seats racists like <person name="james_eastland" occupation="politician">Eastland</person> and his <set group="dixiecrat" type="political_faction">clique</set>, it’s clear to me that they’re
        moving politically, and that one cannot begin to talk morality to people like that. 
    </p>
    
    <p>
        <act cat="non-violence" subcat="questioning">We must question the values of this society</act>, and I maintain that <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> are the best
        people to do that since we have been excluded from that society. we ought to think whether
        or not we want to become a part of that society. That’s precisely what the <org group="sncc" type="cr_group">Student
            Nonviolent Coordinating Committee</org> is doing. We are raising questions about this country. I
        do not want to be a part of the American pie. The American pie means raping South Africa,
        beating Vietnam, beating South America, raping the Philippines, raping every country you’ve
        been in. I don’t want any of your blood money. I don’t want to be part of that system. We
        are the generation who has found this country to be a world power and the wealthiest country
        in the world. We must question whether or not we want this country to continue being the
        wealthiest country in the world at the price of raping everybody else. And because <set group="black" type="race">black
        people</set> are saying we do not now want to become a part of you, we are called reverse racists.
        Ain’t that a gas? 
    </p>
    
    <p> 
        <set group="european" type="race">White society</set> has caused the failure of nonviolence. I was always
        surprised at <set group="quakers" type="denomination" >Quakers</set> who came to Alabama and counseled me to be nonviolent, but didn’t have
        the guts to tell <person name="james_clark" occupation="police_officer">James Clark</person> to be nonviolent. That’s where nonviolence needs to be preached
        — to <person  name="james_clark" occupation="police_officer">Jim Clark</person>, not to <set group="black" type="race">black people</set>. <set group="european" type="race">White people</set> should conduct their nonviolent schools in
        Cicero where they are needed, not among <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> in Mississippi. Six-foot-two men kick
        little <set group="black" type="race">black children</set> in Grenada — can you conduct nonviolent schools there? Can you name on
        <set group="black" type="race">black man</set> today who has killed anybody white and is still alive? Even after a rebellion,
        when some <set group="black" type="race">black brothers</set> throw bricks and bottles, ten thousand of them have to pay the
        price. When the <set group="police" type="law_enforcement">white policeman</set> comes in, anybody who’s black is arrested because we all
        look alike. 
    </p>
    <p> The youth of this country must being to raise those questions. We are
        going to have to change the foreign policy of this country. One of the problems with the
        <cause cat="anti-war">peace movement</cause> is that it is too caught up in Vietnam, and if America pulled out the troops
        from Vietnam this week, next week you’d have to get another <cause cat="anti-war">peace movement</cause> for Santo
        Domingo. We have to hook up with <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> around the world; and that hookup must not
        only be psychological, but real. If South America were to rebel today, and <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> were
        to <act cat="active_resistance" subcat="shoot">shoot the hell out of</act> all the <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> there, as they should, <org group="standard_oil" type="company">Standard Oil</org> would
        crumble tomorrow. If South Africa were to go today, <org group="chase_manhattan" type="company">Chase Manhattan Bank</org> would crumble
        tomorrow. If Zimbabwe, which is called Rhodesia by <set group="european" type="race">white people</set>, were to go tomorrow,
        <org group="general_electric" type="company">General Electric</org> would cave in on the East Coast.
    </p>
    <p> 
        How do we <cause cat="anti-war">stop those institutions
            that are so willing to fight against “Communist aggression”</cause> but close their eyes against
            racist oppression? We’re not talking about a policy of aid or sending <org group="peace_corps" type="foreign_aid_agency">Peace Corps</org> people in
        to teach people how to read and write and build houses while we steal their raw materials
        from them. Because that’s all this country does. What <act cat="non-violent" subcat="education">underdeveloped countries need is
            information about how to become industrialized</act>, so they can keep their raw materials where
        they have them, produce goods, sell them to this country for the price it’s supposed to pay.
        instead, America keeps selling goods back to them for a profit and keeps sending our modern
            day missionaries there, calling them the <org group="peace_corps" type="foreign_aid_agency">sons of Kennedy</org>. And if the youth are going to
        participate in that program, how do you begin to control the <org group="peace_corps" type="foreign_aid_agency">Peace Corps</org>. 
    </p>
    
    <p> This country assumes that if someone ispoor, they are poor because of their own individual
        blight, or because they weren’t born on the right side of town, or they had too many
        children, or went in the <org group="us_military" type="government">army</org> too early, or because their father was a drunk, or they didn’t
        care about school–they made a mistake. That’s a lot of nonsense. Poverty is well calculated
        in this country, and the reason why the poverty program won’t work is because the
            calculators of poverty are administering it. 
    </p>
    
    <p> How can you, as the youth in this country, move to start carrying those things out? Move into the <set group="european" type="race">white community</set>.
        We have developed a movement in the <set group="black" type="race">black community</set>. The white activist has miserably failed to
        develop the movement inside of his community. Will <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> have the courage to go into
        the white communities and start organizing them? That’s the question for the white activist.
        We won’t get caught up in questions about power. This country knows what power is. It knows
        what <cause cat="self-determination">Black Power</cause> is because it deprived <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> of it for over four hundred years.
       <set group="european" type="race">White people</set> associate <cause cat="self-determination">Black Power</cause> with violence because of their own inability to deal with
        blackness. If we had said <cause cat="self-determination">“Negro power”</cause> nobody would get scared. Everybody would support it.
        If we said power for colored people, everybody’d be for that, but it is the word <set group="black" type="race">“black”</set>
        that bothers people in this country, and that’s their problem, not mine. That’s the lie that
        says anything <set group="black" type="race">black</set> is bad. 
    </p>
    
    <p> You’re all a college and university crowd. You’ve taken your basic logic course. You know about major premise, minor premise. People have been
        telling you anything all black is bad. Let’s make that our major premise. 
    </p>
    
    <p> 
        Major premise: Anything all <set  group="black" type="race">black</set> is bad. 
    </p>
    
    <p> 
        Minor premise or particular premise: I am all <set  group="black" type="race">black</set>. 
    </p>
    
    <p> Therefore…I’m never going to be put in that bag; I’m all black and I’m all
        good. Anything all black is not necessarily bad. Anything all black is only bad when you use
        force to keep whites out. Now that’s what <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> have done in this country, and
        they’re projecting their same fears and guilt on us, and we won’t have it. Let them handle
        their own affairs and their own guilt. Let them find their own psychologists. <act cat="non-violent" subcat="non-cooperative">We refuse to
            be the therapy for white society any longer. </act>We have gone stark, raving mad trying to do it.
    </p>
    
    <p> I look at <person name="MLK" occupation="minister">Dr. King</person> on television every single day, and I say to myself:
        “Now there is a man who’s desperately needed in this country. There is a man full of love.
        There is a man full of mercy. There is a man full of compassion.” But every time I see
        <person name="LBJ" occuaption="politician">Lyndon</person> on television, I say, “<person name="MLK" occupation="minister">Martin</person>, baby, you got a long way
        to go.” 
    </p>
    
    <p> If we were to be real and honest, we would have to admit that most people in
        this country see things <set  group="black" type="race">black</set> and <set group="european" type="race">white</set>. We live in a country that’s geared that way. <set group="european" type="race">White</set>
        people would have to admit that they are afraid to go into a black ghetto at night. They’re
        afraid because they’d be “beat up,” “lynched,” “looted,” “cut up,” etc. It happens to black
        people inside the ghetto every day, incidentally. Since <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> are afraid of that,
        they get a man to do it for them — a policeman. Figure his mentality. The first time a black
        man jumps, that <set group="european" type="race">white man</set>’s going to shoot him. <pol>Police brutality</pol> is going to exist on that
        level. The only time I hear people talk about nonviolence is when <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> move to
        defend themselves against <set group="european" type="race">white people</set>. <set group="black" type="race">Black people</set> cut themselves every night in the
        ghetto — nobody talks about nonviolence. <set group="european" type="race">White people</set> beat up <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> every day —
        nobody talks about nonviolence. But as soon as <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> start to move, the double
        standard comes into being. You can’t defend yourself. You show me a <set group="black" type="race">black man</set> who advocates
        aggressive violence who would be able to live in this country. Show him to me. Isn’t it
        hypocritical for <person name="LBJ" occuaption="politician">Lyndon</person> to talk about how you can’t accomplish anything by
        looting and you must accomplish it by the legal ways? What does he know about legality? Ask
        <person name="ho_chi_minh" occupation="politician">Ho Chi Minh</person>. 
    </p>
    
    <p> We must wage a psychological battle on the right for
        <set group="black" type="race">black people</set> to <cause cat="self-determination">define themselves as they see fit</cause>, and organize themselves as they see fit.
        we don’t know whether the <set group="european" type="race">white community</set> will allow for that organizing, because once they
        do they must also allow for the organizing inside their own community. It doesn’t make a
        difference, though — <act cat="active-resistance" subcat="self-determination">we’re going to organize our way.</act> The question is how we’re going to
        organize our way. The question is how we’re going to facilitate those matters, whether it’s
        going to be done with a thousand policemen with submachine guns, or whether it’s going to be
        done in a context where it’s allowed by <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> warding off those policemen. Are white
        people who call themselves activists ready to move into the <set group="european" type="race">white communities</set> on two counts,
        on building new political institutions to destroy the old ones that we have, and to move
        around the concept of <set group="european" type="race">white youth</set> refusing to go into the army? If so, then we can start to
        build a new world. We must urge you to fight now to be the leaders of today, not tomorrow.
        This country is a nation of thieves. It stands on the brink of becoming a nation of
        murderers. We must stop it. We must stop it. 
    </p>
    
    <p> 
        <cause cat="liberation">We are on the move for our liberation.</cause> we’re tired of trying to prove things to <set group="european" type="race">white people</set>.
        We are tired of trying to explain to <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> that we’re not going to hurt them.
        We are concerned with getting the things we want, the things we have to have to be able to function. The question
        is, Will <set group="european" type="race">white people</set> <cause cat="anti-racism">overcome their racism</cause> and allow for that to happen in this
        country? If not, we have no choice but to say very clearly, “Move on over, or we’re going to
        move over you.”
    </p>
    
    <citation> 
        Citation: BlackPast, B. (2010, July 13). (1966) Stokely Carmichael, “Black Power”.
        BlackPast.org.
        https://www.blackpast.org/african-american-history/speeches-african-american-history/1966-stokely-carmichael-black-power/
        Source: So Just, “Speeches on Social Justice”
        http://www.sojust.net/speeches/stokely_carmichael_blackpower.html 
    </citation>
</speech>
