<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speech> (
    <p>1964) JOSEPH JACKSON, “THE VOTE IS THE ONLY EFFECTIVE WEAPON IN THE CIVIL RIGHTS STRUGGLE"</p>
    
    <p> As <org>Christians</org> we are a part of our nation and a part of the struggle of America.
        America was brought into being to satisfy and to answer the human longing for freedom. There
        was the urge in man to be related to other men as men without a modifier or any kind of
        limitation or restriction. There was an awareness of a human kinship deeper than race, more
        profound than nationality, and more inclusive than any accepted religious creed. In addition
        to the quest for a new geographical spot there was a search for a new human relationship, a
        new freedom, and new opportunities. These basic urges inspired the early colonies to brave
        the dangers of a rough and unknown sea, and seek a land in which they could live as free men
        and aspire to the highest possible goals of life without the enslavement of the past or
        being the victims of the determinism of enforced circumstances. They wanted a chance to
        explore and to search out the meaning of life for themselves, and an opportunity to worship
        <pers><per>God</per></pers> according to the dictates of their conscience. 
    </p>
    <p> They soon became convinced that there was no such land, no such Utopia, but all they would find would be an opportunity to
        make such a land and such a country. They were convinced it could be made out of the desires
        that now possessed their souls and out of the thirst for liberty that dominated their lives.
    </p>
    <p> America was born in a struggle and as a struggle for freedom, and for the
        opportunity to develop the highest resources of mankind. The Declaration of Independence and
        the Federal Constitution were the results of our <org>fathers’</org> attempts to put on paper the
        ideals that inspired the birth of the nation, and those principles by which and on which the
        nation was erected and sustained. There have been errors, mistakes, and gross sins committed
        against this American venture, but this high venture has not been repudiated or negated. The
        Massachusetts theocracy became oppressive and hostile toward freedom. Some human beings were
        slain in the episode of the great Witch Hunt. Slavery took its toll, denying to thousands
        the human dignity that <pers><per>God</per></pers> had bestowed upon them; and as a result of the defense of this
        cruel institution, the nation was divided into two armed camps, and a cruel civil war saw
        Americans take the lives of Americans, and brothers shedding their brothers’ blood. But from
        the dust and dirt of this tragic event the American ideals sprang up again with new vigor
        and vitality, and continued its upward march on the rough highway of human history. 
    </p>
    <p> This American venture is powerful but not perfect; ever growing but not grown; and still
        becoming, but is not yet complete. The kind hand of destiny and the benevolent providence of
        <pers>Almighty <per>God</per></pers> have placed the American <org group="Afro-American" type="race">Negro</org> along with other races and nationalities in this
        flowing stream of the nation’s life for which we are justly proud. As patriotic <org>Americans</org> we
        are devoted to our nation’s cause, and are wedded to its ideals and principles. By precept
        and example, by instinct and intuition, we now know the difference between that which is
        truly American and that which is not. We draw a clear distinction between that which is
        germane to the nation’s life and that which is foreign, hostile, and antagonistic to the
        soul of our nation. To the former we pledge our total allegiance and commit every ounce of
        energy, our strength, all of our powers, and even our very lives. But against the latter we
        stand with uncompromising determination, and will not rest until all the enemies of our
        nation have been subdued and conquered. This is the true meaning of the civil rights
        struggle. 
    </p>
    <p> Much time and space is given in the public press to the problem of civil
        rights. It has engaged the minds of our congressmen, and has occasioned many days of debate
        and deliberation. In the name of civil rights thousands have marched through the streets of
        our cities, boycotts have been staged, picket lines have been thrown around places of
        businesses, institutions of learning; and in every nook and corner of the country voices
        have been heard in the defense of and in the interest of civil rights. 
    </p>
    <p> What is this struggle for civil rights? I answer, it is an effort of American citizens to get full
        equality of opportunity. It is the resolution and the determination that there shall be in
        these United States one class of citizens and that is first class citizens. This is a
        struggle to adopt in practice as well as theory the concept of man on which the Declaration
        of Independence is based, and to fully implement the Federal Constitution, one of the
        greatest documents for human freedom since the writing of the Magna Carta. The civil rights
        struggle is a struggle for full freedom, justice, and equality before the law. It is a
        struggle to bring from paper the lofty ideals of America, and to apply them in practice to
        the lives and actions of all Americans. In reality it is America’s struggle to be herself,
        to fulfill the highest promises of her being, and to build a social order after the pattern
        and dreams of our founding fathers and in the light of the wisdom of the ages. 
    </p>
    <p> The civil rights struggle then is not a struggle to negate the high and lofty philosophy of
        American freedom. It is not an attempt to convert the nation into an armed camp or to
        substitute panic and anarchy in the place of law and order. It is in no wise an attempt to
        negate or to amend downward the highest laws of this land proclaiming freedom and justice
        for all. 
        </p>
    <p> The answer is there is a group in the United States that believes that when
        the constitution speaks of the rights of American citizens it meant only men whose skins
        were white. This group believes in segregation as a means of protecting the best interests
        of the nation and of keeping the races separate and pure. But as we look at the degrees of
        pigmentation among all the races in these United States, I ask my <org>segregationist<org> friends,
        don’t you think it is rather late now to talk about the purity of the race; for the blood of
        white <org>segregationist<org>s is in the veins of many whom they would ostracize, and their kinship
        is a biological fact. Many <org>segregationist<org>s fear that granting equality of opportunity to
        people of color will in some way jeopardize their liberties, encroach upon their freedom,
        and threaten their rank, position, and security. But such fear is unfounded if the doctrine
        of American democracy is true. For no free man has any grounds to fear the spread of the
        privileges of true freedom to all men, for the greater the number of free men the more
        secure is freedom and less is the power and danger of oppression. <pers>Abraham Lincoln</pers> sensed
        this fact when he said: “By giving freedom to the slaves we insure freedom to the free.” The
        presence of one bound man pollutes the whole stream of human society; and the rattle of one
        chain of oppression creates a discord that breaks the harmony in every democratic system,
        and disturbs the mind and poisons the heart of every man with fear and dread, so that the
        would-be master finds himself mentally and morally the dweller in the hovels of slaves, the
        servant of a cause that is hostile to democracy, and becomes himself, the victim of the
        baser emotions of his own nature. 
        </p>
    <p> This struggle for civil rights has remained for a hundred years because there are persons among us who are still the victims of the psychology
        of chattel slavery and are yet blinded to the verdict of history and indifferent to the
        logic of life, and in deep rebellion against the voice of <per>God</per>. Some believe that their very
        future and the future well-being of their families depend on keeping alive the cursed demon
        of segregation. In the language of one <org>segregationist<org>: “Yes, we believe in segregation, and
        we will not be changed. We will not be frightened or forced. We will oppose you with every
        ounce of strength that we have. We will fight you from breakfast until noon. We will eat our
        noon-day meal and then re-turn to the field of battle and fight you until sunset. If
        opportunity permits we will catch a bite to eat in the twilight and return to our post and
        fight until the morning comes.” With such determination, with such faith in the way of
        segregation, with such commitment to the evils of discrimination, and with such opponents of
        democracy and freedom, it is no surprise that the struggle for civil rights has remained so
        long and still re-mains one of the grave struggles of the land and country. 
        </p>
    <p> The second reason why the struggle for civil rights has continued is that the segregated does
        not and cannot accept segregation as a way of life. The bound men have read with care the
        great promises of our Federal Constitution, and they have heard clearly the pronouncements
        of statesmen, and have followed the logic of every philosopher of freedom, and they now know
        that segregation and racial discrimination have no logical or legitimate place in the
        American character and constitution. The segregated is just as determined to destroy the
        awful demand of racial segregation as <org>segregationist<org>s are to keep it alive. 
        </p>
    <p> This struggle will continue because of the inner nature of the segregated themselves. There has
        been implanted in the hearts and minds of all men the hope, the love, and expectation of
        freedom, and this inner conviction compels us, and the freedom of soul constrains us so that
        we cannot rest in chains or be at peace in a house of bondage, or compromise with the
        dungeons of discrimination and accept as our lot the cruel and oppressive hand of those
        heartless masters who allow pigmentation of skin to blind them to the inner principles of
        truth and to the revealed purposes of <per>God</per>. The struggle goes on because two determinations
        meet: one; to enslave, and the other; to be free, and here can be no compromise, and from
        the task of solving the problem of freedom there must be no retreat. 
        </p>
    <p> But we as a people must keep ever before us the true meaning of our struggle so that we will never be
        used as tools in the hands of those who love not the nation’s cause but seek the nation’s
        hurt and not our help. Hence there are some things that we must do. 
        </p>
    <p> 1. In our struggle for civil rights we must remain always in the mainstream of American democracy. Our
        cause must never be divorced from the American cause, and our struggle must not be separated
        from the American struggle. We must stick to law and order, for as I have said in the past I
        say now, there are no problems in American life that cannot be solved through commitment to
        the highest laws of our land and in obedience to the American philosophy and way of life. In
        spite of criticisms and not-with-standing threats and open attacks, I have not retreated
        from this position and never will as long as America is the America of the Federal
        Constitution and a land of due process of law. We cannot win our battle through force and
        unreasonable intimidation. As a minority group we cannot win outside of the protection and
        power of the just laws of this land. Read history with open eyes and attentive minds, and we
        will discover that no minority group has and can win in a struggle by the direct
        confrontation of the majority and by employing the same type of pressures and powers that
        the majority possess in abundance. The hope of the minority struggle is with the just laws
        of the land and the moral and constructive forces that are germane to this nation’s life and
        character. 
        </p>
    <p> While we must be determined to achieve the best, we must not be guided by
        a spirit of revenge, blind emotions, and uncontrolled temper. When we act by these baser
        emotions we find ourselves contradicting ourselves. We will deny freedom of speech to those
        who differ with us, and will seek to do the things that will embarrass others however costly
        it may be to us and to them. When we are guided by revenge we do not choose our program of
        action wisely. There are some groups who are thus motivated, will go in, sit in, or lie in,
        in places that have objected to their presence. These same groups when they are dissatisfied
        in places that have accepted them, will give up their achieved rights and walk out in
        protest and revenge. Our actions must be guided both by logic and by law. 
        </p>
    <p> 2. The
        methods that we employ in the present struggle must not lead us into open opposition to the
        laws of the land. In some cases the technique of direct action and demonstrations have led
        to mob violence and to vandalism. At least some who have desired to practice these negative
        methods have used the technique of so-called direct action. 
        </p>
    <p> 3. <org group="Afro-American" type="race">Negro</org>es must become
        registered voters and fight their battles in the polling booth. In the coming campaign we
        must not allow our prejudices, our hatred for individuals, to lead us into emotional
        outbursts and disrespect. The candidates contending for the presidency of the United States
        deserve, and should enjoy, the respect from every American citizen. It is beneath the
        dignity of this fair land of ours to seek to howl down, and to boo from platforms any
        candidate whom we do not favor. We must make choice of the candidate whom we think will
        serve the best interest of this nation and the nation’s cause, and then take our ballot and
        help to elect our choice. As I told this convention in 1956, I tell you again, the ballot is
        our most important weapon. We must not neglect it, forfeit or sell it, but use it for the
        protection of the nation, the promotion of freedom, the promotion of every citizen, and for
        the glory of the United States of America. What I said in 1956 I still say now. 
        </p>
    <p> 4. <org group="Afro-American" type="race">Negroes</org> must still make their own leaders. We must not expect the public press, radio, and
        television to do this job for us. These news media are too busy with other responsibilities
        to be assigned the task of choosing <org group="Afro-American" type="race">Negro</org> leaders to represent the race in these days of
        stress and strain. <org group="Afro-American" type="race">Negroes</org> must not forget that we have many fields in which leaders are
        necessary and important, and we should accept and follow the leaders in their respective
        field; that is, when they are right. We have political leaders, many of whom are worthy of
        our confidence and our respect. We shall follow them and show our appreciation for them. We
        have some dedicated civil rights leaders. We should respect them and follow them in their
        chosen field when they are right. We have religious leaders. We should respect and follow
        them when they are committed to the task of human betterment, human uplift, and the work of
        re-making the social order in the name of justice, righteousness, and peace. 
        </p>
    <p> We have worthy business leaders who can show us the way to improve our economic status, and to
        develop our available economic resources. Let us follow them. We have educators who are
        making their contribution in the field of thought and of mental growth. Let us honor them
        and respect them, and let us not discourage <org group="Afro-American" type="race">Negro</org> educators by advocating directly or
        indirectly, that they are by nature inferior to educators in other racial groups. 
        </p>
    <p> We have athletes and comedians. Let us still applaud our athletes when they achieve on the
        field of competition, and let us join with others and freely laugh at the jokes that our
        comedians give. But we must not confuse these various fields. There must not develop any
        dictatorship of any one field, and athletes and comedians must not make the mistake of
        assuming the role of political, religious, and cultural leaders. We as a race must see to it
        that each man serves in his field, and we must not allow the white community to pick our
        leaders or to tell us what <org group="Afro-American" type="race">Negro</org> we should follow. 
    </p>
    <p> 5. Let us be courageous enough not only to oppose the wrong and the un-American actions in our nation, but we must also
        appreciate and rejoice in the achievements of our nation. There are some recent achievements
        which give us reason for hope, grounds for trust, and basis for rejoicing. 
    </p>
    <p> Ten years ago the Supreme Court of the United States rose above its old concept of separate but equal,
        and declared that segregation had no place in America’s system of public education. This
        year, after a long, hard, and laborious fight, the Congress of the United States passed the
        strongest civil rights bill in its history, and the president signed into law a document
        that said that segregation has no place in American life and destiny. The call is to all of
        us to accept these facts and build on them. We must not ignore the constructive laws of our
        land, we must not organize, condone, or support mobs that parade in the name of freedom. We
        must not turn aside from decency and the constructive American standards in our quest for
        freedom. In our haste let us not be haughty. In our determination we must not become
        detrimental, and in our demonstrations we cannot afford to damn the nation of which we are a
        vital part. 
    </p>
    <p> 6. We have heard much in recent months about direct action in terms of
        boycotts, pickets, sit-ins, and demonstrations of various kinds. In each case the purpose as
        stated is a lofty one; namely, the winning of civil rights and the achievement of the
        equality of opportunity. I repeat, these are worthy ends and desirable goals, but this kind
        of direct action is orientated against others, and for the most part, must be classified in
        the negative since they have been designed to stop, arrest, or hinder certain orderly
        procedures in the interest of civil rights. In some cases however, these actions have been
        against practices and laws considered to be both evil and unjust. 
    </p>
    <p> Today, I call for another type of direct action; that is, direct action in the positive which is orientated
        towards the <org group="Afro-American" type="race">Negro</org>’s ability, talent, genius, and capacity. Let us take our economic
        resources, however insignificant and small, and organize and harness them, not to stop the
        economic growth of others, but to develop our own and to help our own community. If our
        patronage withdrawn from any store or business enterprise will weaken said enterprise, why
        not organize these resources and channel them into producing enterprises that we ourselves
        can direct and control. In the act of boycotting, our best economic talents are not called
        into play, and we ourselves are less productive and seek to render others the same. Why not
        build for ourselves instead of boycotting what others have produced? We must not be guilty
        of possessing the minds and actions of a blind Sampson who pulled a massive building down
        upon him-self as well as his enemies, and died with them in a final act of revenge. 
    </p>
    <p>
        No act of revenge will lift a race from thralldom, and any direct actions that reduce the
        economic strength and life of the community is sure to punish the poor as well as the rich.
        Direct actions that encourage and create more tensions, ill will, hostility, and hate, will
        tend to make more difficult the mental, moral, and spiritual changes essential to new growth
        and creativity in human relations. Remember that when we seek to change certain acquired
        notions and habits of men we are seeking to change that which is very vital in human nature.
        When we labor to change <org>segregationist<org>s and racists who believe they are right, we are
        facing the task of re-conditioning human emotions and building within, new patterns of
        thought, and changing human nature itself. In addition to that type of direct action which
        is negative and aimed at the correction of others, we need the type of direct action also
        that starts with ourselves which tends to produce a higher type of life within us as well as
        within others, and which aims to build a better community in which the available moral
        forces may be used to create new attitudes and new dispositions where human beings will
        regard others as they regard them-selves. 
    </p>
    <p> Why should we expect direct actions against others to bear immediate fruit, and then procrastinate and postpone the direct
        actions that will make us better business men, better statesmen, better thinkers, and better
        men and women with better homes and better fellowship NOW? Now must not only be applied to
        the needs for changes and attitudes of <org>segregationists<org>, it must also be applied to us as as
        people and as a race when we aspire for the best and seek the more constructive and creative
        methods of life. We can be better now. We can acquire a better education now, we can
        organize our capital now and receive our share in this economy of free enterprise now. In
        spite of all that we have attained as a people we have not exhausted our possibilities, and
        the past does not define the limits of our potential. Are we not as well equipped to respond
        to the call of the right, the just, the good, the highest, and the best as are the white
        <org>segregationists<org> against whom we fight? Has not the great <per>God</per> put in our souls the thirst for
        truth and righteousness? Are we not endowed as co-workers with the great creative spirit of
        the universe? Then we need not wait until all is well before we harness our resources and
        venture upon new ways of life and creativity. 
    </p>
    <p> We must not play ourselves too cheap or postpone the day of greater things when the hour of fulfillment is already at hand. To
        the leaders of school boycotts who have called children to remain out of school in order to
        help correct the evils and errors of an imperfect system of education, are you willing now
        to use your influence to lead young people to desert the ranks of drop-outs and struggle now
        to make the best out of the education that is now available? The call to stay out of school
        does not appeal to the highest in students but to the ordinary and the easy. It requires
        less initiative to stay out of school than it does to attend school. It requires less mental
        alertness to refuse to study than it does to study. Is not some education better than no
        education? Of course we should get all the education possible and go as far up the ladder of
        intellectual attainments as our powers will allow us. We must strive for the very best
        opportunities, the best possible schools, and the best possible teachers, but if these are
        not available to us then let us make the best use of what we do have. Remember that the
        future is with the person who knows, thinks, understands, and who has character and soul,
        and who can pro-duce, invest, create and live in harmony with the highest and the best. Of
        course we adults must continue to correct all the evils which make education more difficult.
        We must strive for quality education and seek to make available all the resources possible
        for the education of the young, but our young people must keep their feet in the upward path
        of learning and their minds stayed on the quest for truth. 
    </p>
    <p> The progress of the race lies not in continued street demonstrations, and the liberation of an oppressed people shall
        not come by acts of revenge and retaliation but by the constructive use of all available
        opportunities and a creative expansion of the circumstances of the past into stepping stones
        to higher things. </p>
    
    <citation> Citation: BlackPast, B. (2016, May 25). (1964) Joseph Jackson, “The Vote is the Only
        Effective Weapon in the Civil Rights Struggle”. BlackPast.org.
        https://www.blackpast.org/african-american-history/1964-joseph-jackson-delivered-84th-annual-session-national-baptist-convention-detroit-michigan-sept/
        Sources: TeachingAmericanHistory.org, “Joseph Jackson, Annual Address”
        http://teachingamericanhistory.org/library/document/annual-address/ </citation>
</speech>
