<?xml-model href="../../documentation/Schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<speech title="kaleidoscope_theater_speech" speaker="b_seale" organization="black_panthers" date="1968-04-16" source="arw">
    <!--amz: source link https://americanradioworks.publicradio.org/features/blackspeech/bseale.html-->
    <p>The memorial that we just left  or had  the other day in Oakland, California, in racist USA, was proceeded by a funeral that was held for brother <person name="b_hutton">Bobby Hutton</person>. And at this funeral, one of the preachers there began to get himself uptight and began to check the situation out, doing his best not to do anymore Tomming, stated that there was a man, a little story he's told.</p>

<p>A man who was wandering in the hills and in the woods and he was looking for a spring that was supposed to have clear water where he could get a drink because he was thirsty, he was very very thirsty.</p>

<p>And he found a spring that was very very muddy and dirty and filthy, the water wasn't clear so he began to sit down and try to get in some clear clean water by trying to clear the spring out. He went through all kind of hassles and changes trying to clear the spring out, so he can get him a clear drink of water from the spring.</p>

<p>And another man came along and said, "What are you trying to do?" He said, "I am trying to get a clear drink of water here, I've been thirsty for a long long time and I can't seem to get the dirt and the filth and the mud and the dirt that's here in this spring cleared out to get me a clear drink of water."</p>

<p>The man said, "Well the reason you can't do that," he says "is because on top of the hill about a mile or two back where you haven't checked out yet," he says "there's a hog in the spring." He says "there's a hog in the spring, and a lot of those pigs are running around too in the spring." All we want is a little freedom, all we want is a clear drink of water, but there's a hog in the spring!</p>

    <p>Look, how should we try and how should we work to get the hog out of the spring? Now the spring has been running dirty for a long long time for <set group="vietnamese">peoples in Vietnam</set>, for <set group="africans">peoples in Africa, our black brothers</set>, for <set group="afrolatinos+">our black brothers and colored brothers and sisters in South America and Asia and the Caribbeans etc.</set>, throughout this world.</p>

    <p>Where three-quarters of the world who are non-white who've been brutalized and beaten and exploited and colonialized etc., by this <org group="us_gov">racist power structure here in America</org>. The hog has got to be removed from the spring.</p>

    <p>You can sit by and many times you might say, "Well the spring is really not that dirty." But if you are so close to the hog and have a tendency to sit by and think it's a game that's going on while the hogs and the pigs dirty the spring while you enjoy yourself, looking at the hogs and the pigs dirty the spring where the clear water is, where the freedom is that we want? And you think it's a game, you're jiving and you're shucking, you're shucking yourselves, and these young <org group="black_panthers">Black Panthers</org> here and many others and many many other thousands of people who are joining the party now are concerned with removing that hog from the spring.</p>

    <p>Now how do we do it? For a long long time we struggle. Brother <person name="m_king">Martin Luther King</person> gave us a tactic and this tactic, the tactic that he used was exhausted. And it was exhausted with a racist bullet taking his life.</p>

    <p>Brother <person name="b_hutton">Bobby Hutton</person>, a member of the <org group="black_panthers">Black Panther Party</org> hasn't yet exhausted his means but yet he was killed by the same kind of racist bullet. <org group="us_gov">Pigs. Hungry, exploiting, robbing, thuggish pigs. A whole power structure and all its racism</org>.</p>

    <p>We have to fight it, we have to deal with this hog, we have to deal with this pig, we have to deal with and understand the situation. We have to understand that when <person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> says that power is the ability to define phenomena and make it act in a desired manner, that when <person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> gives this functional definition of power he's talking about power in the real sense. He's not talking about green power which is a shuck.</p>

    <p>Green power? Just ask the question. Green power? As <person name="h_newton">Huey P. Newton</person> teaches he says the <org group="us_gov_1860s">North</org> had <org group="us_gov_1860s">Yankee</org> money and the <org group="csa_gov">South</org> had <org group="csa_gov">Confederate</org> money, both had green power. The <org group="us_gov_1860s">North</org> also had organized guns and force and the <org group="csa_gov">South</org> also had organized guns and force. But the <org group="us_gov_1860s">North</org> uses many many <set group="black_people">black men</set> and <set group="once-slaves">many many slaves, ex-slaves, or slaves</set>, out-maneuvered the <org group="csa_gov">South</org> and had all the guns and force.</p>

    <p>Power is the ability to define phenomena and make it act in the desired manner. The <org group="us_gov_1860s">North</org> defined the <org group="csa_gov">South</org>'s money as not being money anymore and they're burned it in the streets. The only power that was there was the organized guns and force.</p>

<p>It was the organized guns and force, money is only a tool by which power is manipulated. We've seen this happen with the racist white power structure and what it's done to the world.</p>

    <p><org group="us_gov">Racist America</org>, the <org group="zaire_gov">Congo</org> and oppressed people of <org group="apartheid_sAf">South Africa</org>. <set group="revolutionaries">Africa, Liberia, Ghana, Guinea, South America, Cuba</set> where a valiant revolutionary struggle went down. <set group="revolutionaries">China</set> where a most valiant revolutionary struggle went down against all forms of exploitation and is still going down in relation to the world's struggle. Of <set group="black_people">black people</set> and <set group="oppressed">people [who want] to be free</set>. All across this world we can see what racism is doing and all across this world right here in America, you can see what <set group="black_people">black people</set> are getting ready to do.</p>

    <p>To begin to stop racism. Do I have to talk about the fact that <org group="rockefeller_banks">Rockefeller's subsidiaries in banking industries</org> takes out 27 percent of the net profits out of South Africa? Do I have to talk about the fact that 55 percent of the surplus uranium that came to the United States from 1955-1962 come from South Africa while a <set group="black_people">black man</set> works in a mine making $265 a year and a <set group="white_people">white man</set> doing the same damn job makes $3,360 a year? Do we have to go through these facts that are scattered throughout the world these type of examples to get you to understand what's going down?</p>

    <p>Do I have to lay out to you again the platform of the program of the <org group="black_panthers">Black Panther Party</org>? Do I have to get you to understand what we mean by <policy cat="black_liberation">black liberation</policy> in this country? Do we have to get you to understand the necessity of <set group="black_people">black people</set> <act cat="self-defense" subcat="arming">taking up arms to defend themselves</act> against racist attack in this country? Well damn it if I have to do it, we're going to do it. Here we are, alright, come on now!</p>

    <p>Listen, in our program it states, if you haven't read it you begin to read it you begin to understand it. This program is not outlined for the <set group="white_people">white community</set>, it's outlined for the <set group="black_people">black community</set>. Now, number one: <policy cat="self_determination">we want power to determine our own destiny in our own <set group="black_people">black communities</set></policy>. Number two: <policy cat="economic_opportunity">we want full employment for our people</policy>. Number three: <policy cat="housing">we want decent housing fit for shelter of human beings</policy>. Number four: we want an end to the robbery by the white men to the black people in the black communities. Number five: <policy cat="education_early_crt">we want decent education that teaches us about the true nature of this racist decadent system and education that teaches us about our true history and our role in society in the world</policy>. Number six: <policy cat="draft_exemption">we want all black men to be exempt from military service</policy>. [applause] Number seven: <policy cat="end_brutality">we want immediate end of police brutality and murder of black people</policy>. [applause] Number eight: <policy cat="prison_reform">we want all black men and women to be released from county jails, prisons, federal, state, what-have-you because they have not had fair trial, they have been tried by all white juries</policy>. [applause] Number nine: <policy cat="retrial_by_peers">we want all people when brought to trial to be tried in a court by their peer groups or people from their black community</policy> as defined by your jive Constitution of the United States. [applause] Number ten: and in summarization, we want some land, we want some bread, we want some clothing, we want some education, we want some justice, and we want some damn peace.</p>

    <p>If I say I want peace, then you say, "You should put down your gun." But hasn't it occurred to you by now after <cause cat="anti_black_violence">400 years of being brutalized and murdered and lynched and maimed by guns and force on the part of racists and the racist power structure in this country</cause>; it's damn near time <act cat="self_defense" subcat="arming">we picked up the gun to try to begin to get some peace, to defend ourselves and our community</act> from racist attacks by the <org group="police">pigs</org>, to defend ourselves against racist attacks by bird giant saw, Minuteman or <org group="KKK">Ku Klux Klansman</org> or what have you?</p>

<p>Hasn't it occurred to you that it's damn near time we organize ourselves in some fashion to have some ability to begin to make <set group="racists">racists</set> and the racist power structure act in a desired manner as we define the functional definition of what power is? The ability to define the situation and we have been defining it, now we must organize our black communities to also make the power structure of racism act in a desired manner.</p>

    <p>And what is that desired manner? Politics, what is politics? What is politics? You think politics start with a seat in the assembly, no it doesn't. It's related to it but it doesn't start there. Politics starts with <cause cat="need">a hungry stomach</cause>. Politics starts with a <cause cat="police_brutality"><org group="police" op="0">pig</org> crushing us across our skull and murdering our people</cause>. Politics starts with the fact that <cause cat="capitalist_injustice">we get a rotten education and we get brainwashed and fooled in a trick notion and trick knowledge and everything else that goes on in terms of the exploitation that goes down</cause>.</p>

    <p>Politics starts with the fact that <policy cat="needs">you want decent housing, fit for shelter of human beings</policy>, now this is where politics starts. And <set group="black_people">black people</set> now understand with the <org group="Black Panthers" op="5">Black Panther Party</org> that we are going to relate to politics in a real fashion. We are not going for no more jive verbal sincerity at all. Don't give me <person name="r_kennedy">Robert F. Kennedy</person> your jive shuck, "I think it is necessary here, that we come forth." I don't want to hear it.</p>

    <p>I'm tired of my black brother being brainwashed too. "<person name="k_fisher">Kane Fisher</person>, what did you think about <person name="j_kennedy">John F. Kennedy</person> or <person name="r_kennedy">Robert Kennedy</person>?" "Well <person name="a_xx">Andy</person> you know go there boy, I think the boy is going to do something there." Look, we are not going for that thing anymore, <person name="r_kennedy">Robert F. Kennedy</person> was well related to <person name="r_williams">Robert Williams</person> being put in a situation where he had to bent from his country and split because he is being prosecuted by <person name="r_kennedy">Robert F. Kennedy</person>.</p>

    <p><person name="j_kennedy">John F. Kennedy</person>, <person name="j_kennedy">John F. Kennedy</person> did not sent <set group="troops">troops</set> into Birmingham in 1963 until <set group="black_people">black people</set> decided it was necessary for them to defend themselves. When <person name="m_king">Martin Luther King</person>'s motel was bombed and the <set group="racists">racists</set> have been attacking us constantly in that particular area and all over this country, why didn't <person name="j_kennedy">John F. Kennedy</person> send some <set group="troops">troops</set> in there? And he didn't sent <set group="troops">troops</set> until after <set group="black_people">black people</set> decide we're going to defend ourselves from <set group="racists">racists</set>' attacks and went to the streets and whooped up a few <set group="racists">racists</set>' heads then <person name="r_kennedy">Robert</person> and <person name="j_kennedy">John F. Kennedy</person> decide to send it <set group="troops">troops</set>.</p>

<p>See all that verbal sincerity we learn from the past, we learned so we are going to guide our feet by the lamps of the past and we are going to make sure we are going to follow no bags so peace and freedom if you want to do something get down the nitty gritty and don't miss no nits and grits. No more shucking and no more jiving with the McCarthy's with the lynching bag Johnsons with the Governor Reagans and the Robert F. Kennedys right on down the line. No more shucking and jiving!</p>

<p>You want to support black liberation you support the ten-part program of the Black Panther Party, that's what you support.</p>

<p>Freedom, we are not going to sit around and superficially and abstractly trying to define freedom anymore. Black people, the mothers and the scrub nurse since the kitchens that brought the shopping bags home with the leftover ends. The black brothers who try to do their best who struggle in the system, who build railroads to the court system etc. The black brothers and the black young kids coming up, the crap that we get in the context of this racist system.</p>

<p>We are going to define our freedom and we are going to define it by comparing with what we get in the future against what we don't have now. That's the way we are going to define our freedom. [applause] So, you are thrown in a position where you don't sit up to me and talking no more, "I really feel for your situation."</p>

<p>"Uh you know, really now, John, negroes shouldn't be ... but I really feel for your situation." I don't want to hear that crap. I shouldn't be violent. OK, I shouldn't be violent. Some of you are so miseducated. Have we went into your communities and lynched you and murder you? No. Racists have come into our communities throughout this country and lynched and murdered and brutalized us.</p>

<p>Have we went into your neighborhood and intimidated you with any guns? No. Racists, pigs, cops and racists have come in and intimidated and brutalized and murdered us. Did we design this racist power structure system here that exploits and maims black people? No. They designed this to put it against us; we didn't put it on you.</p>

<p>Now the next time you accuse us of racist, you'd better check yourselves and see what the hell you are accusing. The Black Panther Party does not hate anybody because of the color of their skin. That's the game of the Ku Klux Klansman, you check it out.</p>

<p>We will not, we will not stoop to the level of hating a person because of the color of their skin because we understand where racism is manifested. It's not just manifested in some white man sitting in his community and saying, "You know, I don't like black people because of the color of their skin." Racism is manifested in the racist brutal murder and the racist bullet that killed Martin Luther King. The racist bullet that killed Bobby Hutton, the racist bullet that killed Medgar Evers, the racist bullet that has killed and maimed and murdered black people across this country. The lynchings, this is where racism is manifested and you want to know what we hate? That's what we hate with a passion!</p>

<p>So where do you go from there? You look at the Black Panther Party. "Oh, they are going to attack me tomorrow." If you bring a gun down in a black community and started shooting at some black man, the brothers are going to shoot back. I'm sorry, you are going to get buck shots, 120, 00 buck 357 magnums; we're going to vote with what we know.</p>

<p>Now you say we shouldn't, I say we're going to do it whether you like it or not. Now the rest of you that want to start dealing with the power structure on a level where you want to try to change the system get on your gig. You'd better get on your gig because you are jiving. Before Watts, before the black rebellion in Watts that were 1,300 cops. There's a little over 6,000 pigs in this county now. And some 70 percent of them are directly concentrated in black communities controlling black people.</p>

<p>Oakland's pig force has been tripled since three and a half years ago from 350 pigs to over 1,000 pigs. San Francisco doubling, every major metropolis across this country, where black people live the pig forces have been tripled, the national guards have been doubled. Now you check it out  now who are they putting it out there for?</p>

<p>For those of you out in Santa Monica? Don't be foolish. [laughter] They are there for black people with stunner guns and new equipment! You understand politics enough to know that you've got to change that system. When Ronald Reagan sits up and chops up the little chicken fee or welfare programs at the same time, do you remember when he was doing that he increased his highway patrolmen some 1,500? You start thinking about $700 or $800 a month for a highway patrolmen salary a month, add that by 12 and you start thinking about the new cars and the new equipment etc.</p>

<p>And when Los Angeles County asked for 45 or 50 or 200 million dollars for the black communities so they can organize themselves, you know where it went to. It went to the increase of the Gestapo force that Reagan and the rest of these racist bastards and Linden Banes Johnson are putting all over this country.</p>

<p>So this is what we're dealing with. We're dealing with the reality. There's no more time to sit down and continue discussing as to whether or not the racist white wall that black people are chained against is real or not. There's no more time to do that, it's time for you white people to get off in your white communities and begin to end racism and we will deal with it in our communities.</p>

<p>That's where you are going to work at. Don't come down in our communities trying to grow philodendrons and poppies and don't come down in our communities talking about "the basic socioeconomic structure as it's related to the adverse condition that the black people subjected to." Black brothers say, "I don't want to hear this crap, the best thing that you can do is get had because I am thinking about robbing you."</p>

<p>[Because] he don't want to hear it and I don't blame him, so you stay in your own community. 'Cause one of them brothers down there get to seeing you down there, he don't know, some of them ain't running to the Panther Party, and they haven't been instructed yet not to rob you just yet.</p>

<p>The brother hasn't been instructed on the political relationship between you whites and the peace and freedom parties, etc. So don't come down there, we'll take care of our community 'cause we want our power in our community to determine our own destiny [in] our black communities. We want our own black police force chosen by black people, controlled [applause starts] wait a minute, wait a minute, controlled by black people and we're going to make one specific rule that while he's going be a member of the police department chosen from our black community, he's going to have to live in our black community in the areas that he patrols because of this here. If he have to live there, he ain't going to be murdering and committing no police brutality 'cause he's got to come back home and sleep that night.</p>

<p>If that ain't giving a significant symbolic understanding of having power determine your own destiny in your own black community, I don't know what the hell is. That's a very significant point to start with. Point number seven of the program of the Black Panther Party deals specifically with the fact that black people should and do and are forming black self defense groups to defend themselves against racist attacks on the part of the pig department and any other racists who come in our community.</p>

<p>So you see organize black brothers here, ready to do what they have to do to defend themselves against all forms of racists attacks and this is where it's going. This is political. Power comes out of a barrel of a gun and if you don't believe it you're jiving. You see that power structure up there? Where their power come from?</p>

<p>Every time they make a political decision upon any group of people's hair throughout this world or any local country or any local community and the people disagree with that political decision that's been made by the power structure, the power structure sends their guns and force to see to that the political decisions that they've made is carried out.</p>

<p>Black people revolted in Watts, they revolted in Newark, they revolted in Detroit, they revolted all across this country. Rebellions, rebellions rebellions, 150 rebellions before our black brothers death  King  and over 100 some odd rebellions after his death. Those rebellions is the heart and the voice of the people saying that we disagree with the present condition that we are in and these oppressive conditions are caused by the political decisions that have been made on the part of the power structure and each time the power structure mobilizes guns and forces to descend on the people. So what should we do?</p>

<p>Should we go there and sit in and slide in, roll in, jump in, beg in, pray in, wait in, boogaloo in? [laugher] No, because while we are doing all that and while we are singing, "We shall overcome" some pig is keeping a beat on our head. "We [beat] shall [beat] overcome." See what I mean? Crushing our skulls and we sitting there saying, "No, no, no." King has already said that "We shall overcome," so we are going to do it for real  overcome.</p>

<p>Now Mike is going to run for DA here. Mike says he's not a racist, as long as Mike doesn't act in a racist manner, we'll treat him as not acting like a racist, and that's that. We don't have to go through a long dissertation of bull crap, running around, concerning ourselves with whether or not the white wall, the white racist wall that we are chained against is real or not. We are not going to talk about the molecular structure of the wall. [imitating] "You know, the molecular structure of the wall really says you know, that it's really 90 percent space you know. Now is the wall really real or not?" And meanwhile these black men and all these black men up here with their arms chained against the wall saying, "You're damn right it's real. I want to get free from it!" So the brother breaks one of the chains on the right: Newark, Detroit, Watts. Black rebellions across the country every time a brother breaks the chain. Now you are still going to sit down and talking about whether or not the white racist wall is real or not? About the molecular and the atomic structure of it? No you are not going to do it anymore, if you are not going to be a racist you are not 'cause you and I are going to pick up a crowbar and you are going to start prying the rest of those spikes loose. Because we're coming off the wall, we're overcoming, we ain't jiving, it's going to be that way.</p>

<p>Every racist that comes into our community has to be driven out by one means or another, and if you want to aid black liberation you start working on some of them jive legislatures who supposedly represent you who are jiving and shucking. You start working on that. [Applause] And we come over here and say, "Look man, the special race is doing such and such and such and such" and we'll point it out 'cause we can define our situation. You come on down and get down the nitty gritty and don't miss any nits or grits. It's time for you to move. Black people are on the move, all they need is organizing. We're coming, we're coming, we're coming! We're not out-numbered, around this world black people and colored people are not out-numbered, we are out-organized by the racist white power structure.</p>

<p>You are out-organized, anti-draft demonstrators, don't tell me you don't know what police brutality is all about. When you were up there in Oakland in front of the anti-draft office, the draft office that you were demonstrating against it, what did that pig department do? They whoop your heads.</p>

<p>Right down here when they lobby LBJ come down here, they whoop your heads. And then you came to me, a black man that says, "You know what, all that stuff he's talking about police brutality is really real isn't it?" It's real as hell. We've been expressing it for 400 years.</p>

<p>It's real. You disagree with the political decision that the power structure had made, the power structure sending violence and force upon your head. You see that, that it's basic political decision being carried out. You were there non-violently. I mean you weren't violent, you were sitting there, you were going to sit in front of the place real non-violent like and you were going to say, "Well, you just have to arrest me."</p>

<p>The pigs didn't do that, they come down there with force and hit you upside your head. I was sitting in jail looking reading the racist Oakland Tribune, checking you out. I said, "I wonder what they learned." I just wondered. The brothers know. You noticed how you've got them big demonstrations going across the country, you just talk about non-violent, you don't see that many black brothers in there did you.</p>

<p>We've been known for 400 years, we wasn't coming out there, we weren't coming out there at all. Besides the rebellions that we've had in our communities  who knows what them pigs do to us. Look, the platform of the program of the Black Panther Party only outlines the clear drink of water that we wanted freedom. That's all. And we're saying that it's time, that it's time that people move forward to begin to stop racism, begin to deal with it. Now, [imitating] "how do I deal with it?"</p>

<p>Well you've been closer to the racists than we have. Start dealing with it! Learn! How do we deal with the racism that comes up on our heads, we're learning. The other night we learn warfare through warfare from being attacked in Oakland. Our brothers did their best, they had floodlights on that place. They put tear gas in that place and they set a fire in the bottom of the basement, that's what they did. They force some brothers in there by attacking them and the brothers got off in there and went for what they knew.</p>

<p>And we learn warfare through warfare we learn warfare through our brother's death who died for our freedom, because he stuck with it, he believed in it. [When] Bobby Hutton walked out of that house, slightly for it walked out of the house, Eldridge Cleaver told him to take off all his clothes man. Eldridge Cleaver's been in prison before and he was quite hip to the racist system in how they do things.</p>

<p>He says, "Because you going to get killed, if you take off all your clothes," and young Bobby Hutton was just a little too modest and said later for it man and didn't take off all his clothes. And the pigs say, "Now nigger run to the car, the squad car," and before he get there they gunned him down.</p>

<p>Eldridge took off all of his clothes, every stitch, because he said, "If they shoot me and kill me, cause we are being forced out, I don't see how they can shoot across the water in my eyes, I can't see how they can shoot with the floodlights, the tear gasses in here and the fire is burning the place down, I've got to come out."</p>

<p>He says, "So if they kill me, there won't be any bullet holes in my clothes." Eldridge is ready to leave that for that in case he did get murdered, you can understand racism in the real sense! Bobby Hutton left it for us.</p>

<p>Before Bobby Hutton died, before Bobby Hutton died, some five young brothers have been hit in Oakland, killed in Oakland. Young brothers  16, 17, 18 three weeks prior to Bobby Hutton and Bobby Hutton made the 6th murder on the part of the pig department in a period of three, three and a half weeks. So this is the memorial for our black brother Bobby Hutton. Who is Bobby Hutton? Some of you probably might be thinking that we are saying that he's one of the first members that join just because he got killed, that's not true. Bobby Hutton is one of the first members that join. Even before the Black Panther Party was formed we got Bobby Hutton a job at the local poverty program that I was working in that I got fired at because I wouldn't go for the crap that they were putting down.</p>

<p>Bobby Hutton took his money out of his pocket from that $1.35 an hour gig for 30 hours a week and the gig is there to try to make him think that he shouldn't organize against the power structure but think the power structure is beautiful. Bobby Hutton took money out of his pocket to put the first officer.</p>

<p>Huey P. Newton. Look, you read in the paper about a man committing a robbery or something and there's a shootout and someone is killed, you pass it off. But Huey P. Newton was stopped for a traffic ticket! And then a shootout occurred and that's a hell of a large gap that has to be filled especially when he is a political leader in the local community there, especially when we oppose the pig department. We patrol those cops up there with guns and force to make sure no brutality was committed.</p>

<p>Huey P. Newton didn't murder anybody, if we wanted to murder a cop, we could have murdered it way back then, I'm talking about 1966 when we first started. They stopped Huey and held him up for 20 minutes and try to set him up for killing but they lost, the pigs lost.</p>

<p>Twenty minutes for a traffic ticket? It doesn't take 20 minutes to stop a man to give him a traffic citation. So we're going to have a trial in Oakland May 6, that's Huey P. Newton's trial date, 9 a.m. We say we want Huey P. Newton free, May 6, 9 a.m., 12th and Fallon, in Oakland. The national day of black protest to free Huey P. Newton, to free Eldridge Cleaver, to free David Hilliard, to free all the black political prisoners, Rap Brown, all of them, rallied in Oakland, 50,000 in Oakland May the 6! Now how many of you coming up May 6?</p>

<p>Six days of trials, we are going to upset Oakland so bad, we're going to let the power structure know! Black people are going to be in the streets! Black people are going to demonstrate! We can easily tell black people in Oakland to go home, and you know what they do? They go home.</p>

<p>We need to tell black people to go to the streets and you know what they do? They go to the streets. They say all right, the Black Panther Party is where it's at and they want us to lead them politically, we're going to do that. So everybody should be in Oakland May 6, for black protest against the power structure to stand that we want Huey P. Newton to set free, support black liberation, and we want Eldridge Cleaver free etc., 50-100 thousand. Mayor Redding, Governor Reagan, Chief of Police Gaines in the City of Oakland, Cahill of San Francisco are all shook now because we announce the fact that 50 thousand people, 50-100 thousand people are going to be in Oakland.</p>

<p>Now is it so rough that you can't come there? What are you talking about? You demonstrated across this country a million strong. A million strong against the war in Vietnam. Now if you can't get up off your butts to come up there to demonstrate against the war against black people, well you're jiving and you're shucking me.</p>

<p>How many people we going to have up there to say "We are going to stand for free Huey"? You want to stand up and say you're going to be there or you want to sit down and contemplate it? May 6, in the city of Oakland, be there.</p>

<p>Now we want Huey free, we want to see where your money  where your mouth is at. You talk that talk, we'll get on up cause we say we're winner and we are going to move on up. You got it? I want to thank you.</p>
</speech>